<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon, preached before the Right Honourable, Thomas Foote, Lord Maior, and the right worshipfull the aldermen, sheriffs, and severall companies of the City of London. Vpon the generall day of thanksgiving, October the 8. 1650. at Christ-Church, London. / By Doctor Nathanael Homes, teacher of the Church at Mary Staynings, London.</title>
            <author>Homes, Nathanael, 1599-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86504</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2576</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E614_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202565</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862800</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862800</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114976</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86504)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114976)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 94:E614[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon, preached before the Right Honourable, Thomas Foote, Lord Maior, and the right worshipfull the aldermen, sheriffs, and severall companies of the City of London. Vpon the generall day of thanksgiving, October the 8. 1650. at Christ-Church, London. / By Doctor Nathanael Homes, teacher of the Church at Mary Staynings, London.</title>
                  <author>Homes, Nathanael, 1599-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Roycroft, and are to be sold by William Raybould, at the Unicorne, neer the little north doore in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114976:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON, PREACHED Before the Right Honourable, <hi>Thomas Foote,</hi> Lord Maior, and the Right Worſhipfull the Aldermen, Sheriffs, and ſeverall Companies of the City of LONDON.</p>
            <p>Vpon the Generall day of Thankſgiving, <hi>October</hi> the 8. 1650. at <hi>Chriſt-Church, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Doctor</hi> NATHANAEL HOMES, <hi>Teacher of the Church at</hi> Mary Staynings, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Roycroft,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>William Raybould,</hi> at the Unicorne, neer the little North doore in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard, 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:114976:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114976:2"/>
            <head>To the Right honourable, <hi>Thomas Foote,</hi> Lord Maior of <hi>LONDON,</hi> the right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full the Aldermen; together with the Worſhipfull Company of the <hi>Grocers</hi> of the ſayd City.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable, and highly Reſpected;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ACcording to your <hi>deſires,</hi> I have Printed this Sermon; which for your <hi>deſert</hi> (much obliging me) I preſent to you, as in ſpeciall <hi>yours.</hi> Not to be accepted by <hi>all</hi> men, is common to <hi>al.</hi> If <hi>ſome</hi> diſlike, my comfort and recompence is, all do not; <hi>you</hi> are witneſſes. If others be diſpleaſed with what is <hi>common to man</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.*) they forget they are men. If with the <hi>ſubſtance and its relation to the ſolemnity;</hi> they may review, and remember,<note place="margin">And the Prophetin a paſſion (ſay the Learned) ſpake <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruous Hebrew.</hi> Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> I ſpeak againſt ſinne, not men; I advance in my judgment and conſcience (which they ſo plead) the very truth of God: And REGARDED THAT DAY TO THE LORD, as they obſerving it not, ſay, <hi>To the Lord they regarded it not.</hi> And of common equity they owe me this freedom, that I may be as zealous for mine <hi>own</hi> Nation, as they are for <hi>another.</hi> They have their liberty in what is eſſentiall to it (if they pleaſe ſo to keep it) without <hi>coſt or labour.</hi> Wee purchaſe ours (next under God, ſought by prayer) at a great rate in <hi>neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated warrs.</hi> We are not willing to diſturb <hi>their</hi> injoyment, whiles quietly they aquieſce there. If they <hi>doe ours,</hi> whence <hi>theirs</hi> doth ſpring, they wrong <hi>themſelves,</hi> as wel as us. 'Twere happy ſo as to end theſe dividings, if we did enquire into their cauſes. Whether they be not <hi>inſufficient,</hi> and rather to be <hi>removed</hi> from our
<pb facs="tcp:114976:3"/>mindes then our mindes to bee <hi>moved</hi> by them? As whether it be not want of practiſe of what wee profeſſe; Viz. to <hi>be Saints,</hi> and <hi>love Saints,</hi> becauſe <hi>we</hi> be <hi>ſuch,</hi> and <hi>they</hi> be <hi>ſuch?</hi> Or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not a ſuppoſed ty to a part of an obligation, that is now <hi>non-ens;</hi> or to us impoſſible which is much at one <hi>(voluntas non fertur ad impoſſibilia?)</hi> The remainder: <hi>ACCORDING TO THE WORD OF GOD</hi> (put firſt, as the <hi>Baſis</hi> of all) we may ſtill endevour to the utmoſt, and welcome. Or whether it be not an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſſe to promiſe what <hi>all Chriſtians</hi> do, and would in foreine Nations of <hi>Turks, Papiſts,</hi> &amp;c. to ſubmitt quietly to the preſent ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Government? Or whether it be not an hoped content in deſired <hi>future</hi> Governours and Government (of which we have no good experience) rather then in the preſent; preſerved and approved of God by the teſtimony of many glorious wonders? Or whether it be not ſuch an Intereſt of ſome men as is <hi>inconſiſtent with the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> of the State, and is a <hi>Partition Wall</hi> between Chriſtian Brethren? Or it be not a great miſtake; ſuppoſing a violence hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering ſome Members going to ſit in <hi>Councill</hi> ſhould <hi>null</hi> the ſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the reſt that are the <hi>quorum,</hi> contrary to the courſe of all inferiour Courts? Or laſtly, it be not our Non-conſideration of the <hi>Propheſies</hi> and <hi>Promiſes</hi> of the great change of things God is now about to make in our times, and downward, to the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſts Intereſt and Kingdome, whiles we expect things to be as they were? Put in vaine; as this inſuing Treatiſe hints; and may perhaps be ſeconded in other larger Treatiſes, if God permit. The meane whiles, be pleaſed to weigh <hi>this</hi> well; and the Lord bleſſe it to your Honour, and Worſhips, and to all candid Men, who had never ſeen it but for your ſakes, whoſe humble Servant in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Nath: Homes.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study at Mary Staynings,</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, <date>Octob. <hi>21. 1650.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114976:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 149. the laſt Verſe, the later part of the Verſe.</bibl>
                  <p>This honour have all his Saints. Praiſe yee the Lord.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Neerer the Hebrew, thus:</hi> This comely honour to, <hi>or</hi> for all his gracious holy ones, <hi>HAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LELU-JAH.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS day, and this Text (I truſt) are well met: They both intend praiſe. They both reciprocally congratulate one another in that thing: The day (I doubt not) welcomes the Text, and the Text will, ſurely, ſerve the day, in ſeverall weighty conſiderations. You ſee 'tis in one of the Pſalmes, called in <hi>Hebrew</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tehillim,</hi> PRAYSES. Of which, this is a ſinguler one. The firſt word it ſpeakes, is, <hi>Praiſe yee the Lord;</hi> and the laſt breath it breaths is, <hi>Praiſe yee the Lord:</hi> Both, both the firſt and the laſt is in the Hebrew, HALLELU-JAH. Juſt the praiſefull language of Gods holy people, throughout the Revelation, <hi>Viz.</hi> HALLELU-JAH, HALLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LU-JAH, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and relating to OUR times, and downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to Chriſts <hi>reſtoring all things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 1.6. Act. 3.21.</note> For then are Gods words fulfilled, when they appeare in deeds. THEN is fulfilled the Propheticall part of this <hi>Pſalme;</hi> namely, <hi>That God will beautifie the meeke,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> with <hi>ſafety</hi> as well as <hi>Salvation</hi> (<hi>Verſ.</hi> 4.) <hi>and will give a ſpeciall honour to all his Saints,</hi> or <hi>holy ones</hi> (<hi>Verſe</hi> of the Text) WHEN (<hi>Verſ.</hi> 6.) he puts the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114976:4"/>
               <hi>high praiſes of God in their mouth,</hi> or deeper <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in their throats,</hi> whiles a TWO-EDGED SWORD is in their HAND, to execute (<hi>Verſ.</hi> 7.) vengeance on (the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> ſayes your Tranſlation) <hi>the Nations,</hi> ſaith the Hebrew, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> be they what <hi>peoples</hi> they will be, that hate the <hi>Saints,</hi> as it follows (<hi>Verſ.</hi> 7.) <hi>and to execute puniſhments,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> on the PEOPLES (in the Plurall Number) and (<hi>Verſ.</hi> 8.) <hi>to binde their Kings with Chaines, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with Fetters of Iron, and to execute the judgement that is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</hi> THEN I ſay, <hi>ſo much</hi> of the <hi>propheticall</hi> part of this Pſalme is fulfilled, <hi>as much</hi> as that is done; be it <hi>now</hi> much, or more <hi>hereafter;</hi> and therefore now <hi>to praiſe</hi> with the Holy ones in the Revelation, ſaying, HALLELU-JAH. For into thoſe times we are thus farr run, as to be at leaſt under the <hi>ſixth Seale, ſixth Trumpet of that Seale, and under the end of the fourth Vial of that Trumpet,</hi> if not further; namely under the <hi>beginning of the fifth Vial.</hi> For according to <hi>Revel. Chap.</hi> 16. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>A Vial hath been poured out upon the Sun;</hi> that is, Sore afflictions of Warr, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon the moſt ſplendid <hi>body</hi> (for Goſpell light) of the <hi>Chriſtian World,</hi> as <hi>Low-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, Germany, England, Wales, Ireland;</hi> and ſince that, <hi>power hath been given to this Sun, to ſcorch men;</hi> that is, To afflict them ſorely, <hi>that poured the Vial of wrath upon this Sun,</hi> till, in ſtead of repentance for afflicting the <hi>Sun,</hi> they <hi>blaſpheme.</hi> And moreover there hath been ſome droppings of the fifth Viall upon the <hi>Throne of the Beaſt, Turke</hi> and <hi>Pope</hi> (for they are in many reſpects <hi>one,</hi> as wee have elſewhere demonſtrated, though different parts of the whole, the <hi>Pope</hi> being the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall head, from whom the <hi>Turke</hi> as a maſter limbe, derived, partly his <hi>blood,</hi> partly his <hi>Religion,</hi> and partly his <hi>Territories,</hi> pulling three hornes from the ten) I ſay upon the <hi>Throne of the Beaſt,</hi> in <hi>Candia, Brazil, Portugal, Spaine, France, &amp;c.</hi> For the <hi>throne of the Beaſt</hi> here (which few obſerve) doth not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114976:4"/>ſignifie the <hi>individuall City</hi> and place where the Beaſt ſits, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in materiall, or ſpirituall <hi>Babylon;</hi> for preſently tis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to be his <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and was onely filled with <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> not with utter ruine. The ruine of the great City <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> is not till the ſeventh Viall (<hi>Verſ.</hi> 19.) For this the people of that time are typified and <hi>propeſied</hi> to praiſe with <hi>Hallehu-jah;</hi> for incontinently and continuedly the <hi>judgement</hi> of the Beaſt is <hi>threatned</hi> (<hi>Chap.</hi> 17.) <hi>deſcribed</hi> (<hi>Chap.</hi> 18.) and <hi>executed</hi> (<hi>Verſ.</hi> 19.) where in the Preface you have five times over <hi>Hallelu-jah:</hi> And here the people are <hi>commanded</hi> to praiſe with <hi>Hallelu-jah.</hi> Which <hi>Hallelu-jah</hi> is two diſtinct words, ſignifying, <hi>Praiſe yee JAH,</hi> which <hi>JAH</hi> is an uſuall Hebrew contract of JEHOVAH, who is the <hi>Objectum quod,</hi> the HE, or <hi>perſon</hi> that is to be praiſed; namely, the <hi>Great God;</hi> according to which name of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> hee moſt makes himſelf <hi>known,</hi> and moſt loves to be owned in working <hi>wonders</hi> of deliverance, which are the Signal of <hi>Jehovah. Ex.</hi> 6.2 <hi>&amp;c. I am Jehovah</hi> (ſo in Heb.) <hi>I appeared to Abraham, Iſaac, and Jacob by the name of God Almighty, but by the name Jehovah was I not known unto them; wherfore ſay unto the children of Iſrael, I am Jehovah</hi> (ſo in the Hebrew) <hi>and I will bring you out from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the burdens of the Aegyptians, &amp;c.</hi> A wonderfull undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in the condition the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were now in. But this is the deſigne, to interpret and demonſtrate God as a <hi>Jehovah.</hi> For it ſignifies God moſt true, powerfull, and faithfull, in <hi>being, ſaying, and doing:</hi> The which is <hi>ſealed</hi> to be ſo when God workes exployts of Victory for the delivery of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which is made more plaine by that, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.14. <q>
                  <hi>And God ſayd unto Moſes, I am that I am;</hi> and he ſayd, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſay unto the children of Iſrael, I AM hath ſent me unto you</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an alluſion and derivation of the name <hi>Jehovah</hi>) <hi rend="margQuotes">to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you he will do this ſtrange thing of delivering you out of Egypt, how unlikely ſoever it ſeemes, as is the effect of the Chapter following.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:114976:5"/>
            <p>But <hi>who</hi> muſt praiſe; according to the ſhrill emphaſis on <hi>YEE, Praiſe YEE the Lord?</hi> The <hi>Subjectum</hi> (as I may ſay) <hi>qui, Viz. They</hi> that muſt praiſe, are thoſe to whom this <hi>Yee</hi> relates, named afore in the Pſalme under ſeverall titles. Who in the generall are expreſt by HIS, that is, Such as are Gods owne, godly perſons, Gods peculiar: Others cannot if they will, or <hi>will not</hi> if they can. In particular, in the fourth Verſe, they are called <hi>His people;</hi> in the Text, his <hi>Saints,</hi> or <hi>Ho'y ones:</hi> both materially are the ſame. All <hi>his people</hi> are <hi>Saints,</hi> and all his Saints are <hi>his people:</hi> But formally and preciſely, they are two diſtinct notions, full of ſenſe and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis, to the <hi>intent</hi> of the propheſie of this Pſalme, and to the <hi>event</hi> of that propheſie as it now appeares begun to be fulfilled. <hi>Saints</hi> preciſely taken, is their <hi>ſpirituall</hi> notion, <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tethetically</hi> diſtinguiſhing them from <hi>Nations and Peoples,</hi> on whom theſe <hi>Saints</hi> muſt <hi>execute vengeance and puniſhment, Verſ.</hi> 17. And <hi>people</hi> as preciſely diſtinguiſhed, is their <hi>civill</hi> notion putting them in full <hi>contra-diſtinction,</hi> and flat op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition over againſt <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Nobles,</hi> who are to be <hi>bound and fettered by this holy people,</hi> as <hi>people, Verſ.</hi> 8. For though we inſiſt not upon the ſuppoſition of ſome, that this Pſalme was penned whiles the <hi>Jewes</hi> were in ſome Captivity, or bondage, into which condition they were once and againe precipitated by the ill rule of their <hi>Kings;</hi> this is cleere in the Pſalme, that they are here propheſied and preſcribed to <hi>be joyfull in God their King, Verſ.</hi> 2. (a Monarch that never degenerates) and in ſtead of being <hi>bound</hi> to Kings and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and be judged by them, <hi>to binde Kings with chaines, and Nobles with Fetters of Iron, and execute judgement on them, Verſ.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>But for what muſt they praiſe? <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <hi>Objectum quo.</hi> the thing, in, by, and for which, they ſhall praiſe in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>matter,</hi> is, <hi>Honour:</hi> In the ſpecificating <hi>formes</hi> (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114976:5"/>with great emphaſis) is <hi>Such Honour;</hi> namely, That the <hi>Holy people</hi> of the Lord ſhall execute vengeance upon all Nations, and peoples that are Enemies to them, <hi>as ſuch,</hi> and <hi>binde their Kings and Nobles,</hi> though never ſo much cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up by <hi>thoſe peoples and Nations.</hi> For thoſe Princes and Peoples, Nobles and Nations, ſhall fall together before the <hi>holy people,</hi> who ſhall <hi>execute upon them the judgement THAT IS WRITTEN;</hi> that is, Written in the Propheſies of the Old Teſtament; as <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.1, 2. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.26, 27. And this <hi>Honour</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to and for all his <hi>Saints</hi> ſucceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, mediately or immediately, one way or another, having an hand in that ſubduing of Kings and Peoples, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Either by <hi>Authority</hi> of Councils, or <hi>power</hi> of Armies, or proviſions for both, or prayers for all. For this <hi>ſubduing</hi> is not here meant to be meerely <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> but mainely <hi>corporall.</hi> For firſt, if thoſe Kings, Nobles, and Nations, be unconvinced <hi>ſpiritually,</hi> then they are not ſubdued, or overcome, but doe overcome, and with contempt of the <hi>Holy people.</hi> If they be ſo convinced, then they are of the Freedome, and partake of the <hi>Honour</hi> of the <hi>Holy people,</hi> to <hi>binde and puniſh the Kings, Nobles, and Nations, that are obſtinate.</hi> Secondly, Tis not ſayd, a <hi>Two-edged Sword</hi> in their MOUTH, as to ſignifie the <hi>Sword</hi> of the <hi>ſpirit;</hi> but tis ſayd, <hi>A two-edged ſword in their HAND.</hi> Thirdly, Nor is it ſayd onely, <hi>A two-edged ſword</hi> in their hand, but alſo tis intimated that they have <hi>Chaines, yea Fetters of Iron</hi> in their hands, wherewith <hi>to binde, &amp;c.</hi> Fourthly, That that is ſayd to be in their Mouth, is the <hi>exaltations of God</hi> (as tis in the Hebrew) that is, The Word, and prayer, and prayſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereby they ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually extoll God, and labour to convince and convert the oppoſite peoples, and Princes, who ſtanding out, the <hi>ſword, and Fetters, and chaines, muſt take place.</hi> For though in acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate conſideration, <hi>Promotio adjumenti,</hi> the preciſe immediate
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114976:6"/>
               <hi>meanes</hi> to <hi>ſet up</hi> the Kingdome of Chriſt, be <hi>ſpirituall;</hi> yet <hi>Remotio impedimenti,</hi> the removall of impediments, the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the obſtinate enemies that deſpiſe the Word, muſt be by the <hi>Sword.</hi> And in this alſo the ſpirituall meanes, <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately</hi> muſt have an hand; teaching and incouraging the Conquerours to their duty. Of which the Text is not ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, whiles it puts the <hi>Sword</hi> into the hands of an <hi>holy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that can doe nothing <hi>againſt the Word, but for the Word.</hi> Fifthly, To be converted or convinced by ſpirituall meanes to comply with the Holy people, is not a <hi>judgement, puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or vengeance,</hi> according to the language of the Text; but an high <hi>mercy.</hi> Sixthly, Add to all, that God hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, not onely of late, but anciently fulfilled this Text <hi>literally,</hi> to make his Holy people ſubdue Kings, Nobles, and Nations; 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.21. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. with many inſtances in the Old Teſtament; and promiſes, yea Propheſies, hee will doe likewiſe for future; of which the <hi>Revelation</hi> is full, as we ſhall hint by and by.</p>
            <p>From all, with all care, thus explained, this Doctrinall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation naturally ſprings up.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>The Lord Jehovah performing his promiſe of honouring his Holy people to be inſtrumentall in the overthrow of Kings, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and Nations, their enemies; commands thoſe his holy people reciprocally to praiſe him.</hi> For <hi>illation</hi> and <hi>inference,</hi> tis ſo ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Text, that he that ſees the one, ſees the other. And agreeably to the Text, the Doctrine ſounds of a holy people <hi>armed,</hi> as well as the Text. For <hi>confirmation,</hi> you cannot but ſee by this time that the Doctrine is the abſolute quinteſſence of the Text, and the inmoſt minde of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoule thereof; and that the Pſalme it ſelfe, if looked on but <hi>Narratively</hi> is in the head and heel thereof, the <hi>Saints duty of praiſe;</hi> and in the middle, the heart and liver that mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter good blood and life ſpirits, to nouriſh that praiſe, is,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114976:6"/>The <hi>dignities of victories, and vengeance and judgements of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity on oppoſing princes and peoples,</hi> that the Saints ſhall attain unto. But if this Pſalme be looked upon <hi>prophetically,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the proper nature, idiom, and very minde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we ſhall finde it to have a long proſpect; terminated with nothing but the full ſalvation and ſettlement of Jews and Gentiles, into a moſt glorious Church. So that if in part it be fulfilled in any eminent atchievements afore that, they are but types, one greater then another, of ſome grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thing to come at laſt. They are but as <hi>panelia,</hi> ſeverall Images of the Sun, formed in the upper elements, the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker or dimmer next us, whereby we look to the next which is brighter, and ſo at laſt to the Sun it ſelfe. They are but ſeverall marches of the <hi>Holy Army</hi> of the Lord of Hoſts; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall <hi>Forlorne Hopes,</hi> and Parties, ſkirmiſhing and conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, before the whole Field be won in a ſet Battalio.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Iſrael,</hi> new delivered from <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in <hi>AEgypt;</hi> now marching in the Wilderneſſe towards <hi>Canaan,</hi> praying and fighting againſt <hi>Amaleck</hi> (aſſaulting them) utterly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrowing <hi>Amaleck</hi> in a pitcht Battell (<hi>Exod.</hi> 17.) 'tis written in tables (<hi>Exod.</hi> 20.) <hi>I am the Lord thy God that brought thee out of the Land of AEgipt;</hi> which they carried with them as their <hi>Motto</hi> in a <hi>Standard,</hi> to preſignifie to them, what God would in future do for them, and by them, againſt the Kings and Nations, in their way towards, and in <hi>Canaan;</hi> and therefore they ſhould obey his Commandements. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly God againe appearing for them, inabling them to conquer ſeverall Kings and their Nations, as they marched on towards <hi>Canaan;</hi> to wit, <hi>Sihon</hi> King of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> and <hi>Og</hi> the King of <hi>Baſhan</hi> (<hi>Numb.</hi> 21.) as after, the Kings and Nations in <hi>Canaan</hi> (as we have it in the Book of <hi>Joſhuah</hi>) 'tis put upon record, and turned into a Divine <hi>Act,</hi> or <hi>Law</hi> (ſtill in force, unrepealed, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 136.) to command all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114976:7"/>Saints in the <hi>preſent Tenſe,</hi> in their ſeverall generations, <hi>then in preſent</hi> being, three times together in the beginning of that Pſalme, <hi>Hodu, Hodu, Hodu,</hi> that is, <hi>O now give thanks, O now give thanks, O now give thanks unto the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> deſcanting the <hi>wherefore,</hi> the <hi>cauſes, Viz.</hi> the Victories aforeſayd, in <hi>parts;</hi> to wit, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 18. <hi>&amp;c. O give thanks to him which ſmote great Kings, for his mercy endures for ever: And ſlew famous Kings, for his mercy endures for ever</hi> (which conveniently compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the Kings in <hi>Canaan,</hi> having ſpoken of the overthrow of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of <hi>AEgypt</hi> afore, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 15. And then nameth the Kings whom Iſrael overthrew afore they came into <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi>) <hi>He ſlew Sihon the King of the Amorites, for his mercy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth for ever; And Og the King of Baſhan, for his mercy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures for ever. And gave their Land for an heritage, for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy endureth for ever. Even an heritage to Iſrael, for his mercy endures for ever. Who remembred us in our Low eſtate, for his mercy endures for ever. And hath Redeemed us from our Enemies, for his mercy endures for ever.</hi> As if the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſhould ſay, Theſe performances are pledges that Gods <hi>mercy endureth for ever,</hi> to make his people doe the <hi>like exploytes in future Ages.</hi> Which very thing of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Conqueſts, unto the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> extends (as the true intent thereof) downe to all Ages, till the <hi>Saints,</hi> or <hi>Holy people</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the <hi>Great reſt</hi> of all; Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes, Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. Where evidently, the Apoſtles deſigne is to prove, that to that day, wherein he wrote to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes,</hi> there remained yet a <hi>Reſt</hi> for <hi>them, &amp;c.</hi> that were the <hi>people of God.</hi> How doth the Apoſtle prove it? With what premiſes? Marke, he layes downe two: Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God <hi>inſtituted a reſt for his people from the creation;</hi> But that was but weekly, <hi>Viz.</hi> the ſeventh day: <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4. <hi>For hee ſpake in a certaine place of the ſeventh day on this wiſe, and God did reſt the ſeventh day from all his workes.</hi> Secondly, Becauſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114976:7"/>God did give them a certain <hi>reſt in Canaan</hi> for ſome hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of years, by <hi>Joſhua,</hi> v. 8. by <hi>Jeſus,</hi> that is, <hi>Joſhua;</hi> ſo in your margin in your Bibles: But that reſt alſo was but for a time: and ſince all this, God ſpeaks of <hi>another reſt,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6, 7. namely, by <hi>David,</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95. that people ſhould not <hi>harden their hearts, to hinder them from</hi> entering into his <hi>reſt.</hi> From all which premiſes, the Apoſtle ſolemnly concludes, v. 9. <hi>THERE REMAINETH THERE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORE A REST TO THE PEOPLE OF GOD.</hi> As if the Apoſtle ſhould have ſaid (for they that have their eyes open and acute, can make no leſs of it) that the former <hi>RESTS,</hi> and in particular, that in <hi>Ganaan,</hi> were but <hi>types</hi> of a greater <hi>Reſt</hi> on earth.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> For the Apoſtle cannot mean by <hi>Reſt</hi> or <hi>SABBA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TISM</hi> (as he calls it in the Greek) the ſtate of <hi>ſupernal glory,</hi> as we have demonſtrated in another Treatiſe; but (to adde one word now) he calling this Reſt <hi>THE WORLD TO COME,</hi> names it in the Greek with great emphaſis,<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 2.5 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>That INHABITED WORLD that is to come.</hi> (I ſpeak ſhort in this, becauſe I have been large in another Treatiſe, which I hope the world ſhall ſee ere long.) And this name of the <hi>world,</hi> when the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the <hi>world to come,</hi> is the name uſed to ſignifie the world when 'tis ſaid <hi>all the world was to be taxed,</hi> Luk. 2.1.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> So that 'tis the <hi>ſame world</hi> wherein the <hi>holy people</hi> ſhall have a <hi>better reſt</hi> then ever they had; onely 'tis, ſaith the Apoſtle, a <hi>world to come;</hi> as if the world did <hi>newly begin,</hi> by the deſtruction of the <hi>old world</hi> of all the obſtinate enemies againſt the Saints, which the <hi>holy people</hi> ſhall ſubdue or deſtroy: juſt as we ſay the <hi>old world</hi> afore the Flood. And <hi>Melchizedek</hi> (that is,<note place="margin">H. b. 7.3.</note> 
               <hi>Son</hi> the ſon of <hi>Noah</hi>) is ſaid to be <hi>without beginning of days and end of life,</hi> becauſe he lived many yeers in <hi>both worlds,</hi> that is, in the <hi>old</hi> before the ſlood, and in the <hi>new</hi> after the flood. If we cannot yet ſee (and that were ſtrange if we cannot) that every great deliverance of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114976:8"/>the <hi>Holy people</hi> is a type of a future greater; and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, that <hi>Joſhua</hi> and his holy Army were a Type of greater Victories yet to come ſince the Apoſtles, to wit, more <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> and <hi>effectual;</hi> then conſult with <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1.5. compared with <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.5, 6. In that of <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> the words are to <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> and in relation to his <hi>Wars</hi> againſt the Kings and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Canaan. There ſhall not any man be able to ſtand before thee, all the days of thy life: as I was with Moſes, ſo will I be with thee.</hi> (See how there alſo is an intimation of one mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to be a type and pledge of another. But the laſt words I aim at, <hi>viz.</hi>) <hi>I will not fail thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> Theſe laſt words, to confirm the former in the buſineſs of conqueſt in War to and by <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> are applied, in <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5, 6. to all the <hi>holy people,</hi> in all their wars, and wants, and difficulties what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, with a non-ſuch or unparallell'd vehemency of ſpeech, in five <hi>Negatives,</hi> (in the Greek) <hi>Let your converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be without greedineſs after ſilver,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and <hi>be content,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for he hath ſaid, I will NEVER LEAVE THEE, NOR FORSAKE THEE: ſo that we may boldly ſay, The Lord is my helper, and I will not fear what man ſhall do unto me.</hi> Which laſt words, ſound of help in <hi>Wars;</hi> and oppoſitions of men; as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, of all other ſupplies. And then preſently gives us an experiment how well God hath dealt with his people of <hi>godly converſation</hi> in all ages. And then addes a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all; namely, becauſe <hi>Chriſt is yesterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever;</hi> viz. <hi>unchangeable,</hi> to deal in the ſame gracious way with all his people in all ages. Thus you ſee how in the Old Teſtament former victories and deliverances were types and pledges of future.</p>
            <p>The ſame alſo will plainly appear in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> by S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> the peculiar Prophet and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies for our times; who carries on the meaning of the <hi>holy Peoples</hi> exploits in the Old Teſtament, in all their <hi>warlike
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114976:8"/>victories,</hi> to be Typical and praemitial, patterns and pledges of future greater things that the holy people ſhall do and attain in our times and downward. For the manner of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> lying in Camp in expeditions of War, was, the <hi>Ark</hi> in the middle; the four and twenty Orders of their <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> round that; and the whole <hi>body of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> round them, in four Brigades, three Tribes to a Brigade or Poſt, towards the four Quarters of heaven. And the firſt Tribe of each Brigade or Squadron, conſiſting (I ſay) of three, did bear the Standard for all three. And the four Standards or Colours of the four Brigades, were, A <hi>Lion,</hi> an <hi>Ox</hi> or <hi>Calf,</hi> the <hi>Face of a man,</hi> and a <hi>Flying eagle</hi> (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears both by Scripture<note n="*" place="margin">Ezek. 1.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Compare M. <hi>Mede</hi> on <hi>Rev.</hi> 4. now tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated in Engliſh.</note>, and Jewiſh Antiquities*, which I cannot now ſtay to diſcuſs.) And thus, juſt, doth S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in the <hi>Revelation</hi> bring in the holy people in the like poſture, conquering and praiſing, in our times, and downwards. So in <hi>Level.</hi> 4.8.9, 10. the <hi>Throne,</hi> anſwerable to the <hi>Ark,</hi> is in the <hi>middle.</hi> And the <hi>four Beaſts</hi> (Greek, <hi>Animals</hi>) that is, the <hi>whole Camp of the holy people,</hi> or Hoſt of God, ſignified by four Beaſts or Animals that antiently was in the Iſraelites Standards or Colours, <hi>reſt not praiſing, ſaying, Holy, holy, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lord God Almighty, which was, and is, and is to come.</hi> Mark how the praiſe refers to Gods <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>holineſs,</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeableneſs,</hi> to <hi>hate the unholy,</hi> and ſo <hi>from time to time</hi> to <hi>impower,</hi> his holy people to conquer the unholy, their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. And when the four <hi>Animals,</hi> the <hi>Camp of the people of God,</hi> once begin their <hi>Anthem</hi> in the Chore, then preſently the <hi>four and twenty Elders,</hi> the <hi>Godly Miniſtery</hi> ſee cauſe, and ſolemnly ſing or praiſe. <hi>And when thoſe Beaſts give glory, and honour, and thanks to him that ſate on the throne, who liveth</hi> FOR EVER AND EVER, (obſerve ſtill how Gods <hi>power</hi> and <hi>unchangeableneſs</hi> is minded) <hi>the four and twenty Elders fall down before him that ſate upon the Throne, and worſhip him that liveth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114976:9"/>for ever,</hi> &amp;c. You ſee yet ſtill the praiſe hath a ſpecial eye to Gods <hi>power,</hi> keeping the throne, and his <hi>immutability,</hi> living for <hi>ever;</hi> intimating, God would ſtill be the ſame to his holy people, and more and more to make them ſubdue all their enemies. Which is ſo often repeated, becauſe 'tis the <hi>main propoſition of the whole book of the Revelation,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne</hi> of Chriſt for his people. <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7, 8. (Studie it well.) Which, and our particular in hand, is again repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to us in <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. where the <hi>holy people,</hi> the Hoſt of the Lord of Hoſts is muſtered <hi>one hundred fourty and four thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, and Auxiliaries without number, with palms in their hands,</hi> (ſignals of Victory) <hi>praiſing, ſaying, Salvation to our God who ſits on the Throne, and to the Lamb. And all the Angels ſtood round about the Throne, and about the</hi> ELDERS, <hi>and the four Beasts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and worſhipped, ſaying, Amen: bleſsing, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and wiſdom, and thankſgiving, and honour, and power, and</hi> MIGHT, <hi>be unto our God for</hi> EVER <hi>and</hi> EVER. <hi>Amers.</hi> (Still Gods <hi>power</hi> and <hi>authority</hi> is minded.) And in what garb and poſture do theſe praiſe: <hi>Anſw.</hi> In the foreſaid manner of <hi>four Animals,</hi> repreſenting the <hi>Camp of Gods holy people,</hi> with their <hi>Miniſters,</hi> ſignified in the <hi>four and twenty Elders,</hi> v. 11.</p>
            <p>If you ſay theſe places are dim for the thing urged, and that light that is in them glimmers rather of <hi>ſpiritual</hi> wars and victories, then <hi>corporal;</hi> we will give you ſome plainer places, and for the literal ſence of corporal victories as well as ſpiritual. The firſt place ſhall be in the fifth Chapter of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> conveniently placed between the fourth and ſeventh afore alleadged, the better to expound them. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.1. God is brought in <hi>on the Throne,</hi> ſutable to the <hi>Ark</hi> in the middle of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amp of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and to ſignifie his <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> and <hi>preſence</hi> with his holy people; and <hi>Chriſt at his right hand,</hi> to tell us his minde, and to prevail with him
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114976:9"/>for our aſſiſtance. For which (typified in the <hi>opening of a book</hi>) <hi>the four Beaſts or Animals, and the four and twenty Elders,</hi> (whoſe ſignification you have heard already) <hi>fall down</hi> in prayer-wiſe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8, &amp;c. <hi>ſinging a new ſong</hi> (that is, for new mercies, as v. 1. before my Text) <hi>ſaying, Thou art wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to take the book, and open the ſeals: for thou waſt ſlain, and haſt redcemed us to God by thy blood,</hi> &amp;c. (there is our <hi>ſpiritual</hi> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories) <hi>and haſt made us to our God Kings and Prieſts, and we ſhall reign on the</hi> EARTH. <hi>On</hi> the earth,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is more then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> See alſo the Syr. &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rai, Bio. Gall.</note> not onely <hi>in</hi> the earth. The <hi>Syrtack</hi> and <hi>Arabian</hi> Tranſlation is <hi>over</hi> the earth. Here plainly is the holy peoples <hi>corporal</hi> victories. We will pin this yet faſter with that in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.11, &amp;c. <hi>The Witneſſes roſe and ſtood on their feet, and great fear fell on them that ſaw them. The ſeventh Angel ſounds, and then the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of</hi> THIS WORLD <hi>are become the Kingdom of our Lord, and of his Chriſt. And the four and twenty elders praiſed, ſaying, We give thee thanks, O Lord God Almighty, which art, and wast, and art to come, that thou haſt taken to thee thy great power, and haſt reigned: and the Nations were ANGRY.</hi> All which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be compatible and conſiſtent with <hi>ſupernal glory,</hi> or the ultimate Judgement, but with a ſtate on earth afore. We will trouble you but with the naming of two places more, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. verſ. 1. to 9. The <hi>Camp</hi> of Gods <hi>holy people,</hi> to the number of <hi>one hundred fourty and four thouſand, marked in the forehead</hi> (not without alluſion to the ancient marking of <hi>ſouldiers</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">So the Rom. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiqu.</note>) <hi>and under the notion of four and twenty elders, and the four Animals,</hi> ſing a <hi>new ſong</hi> of <hi>praiſe to God</hi> for <hi>the fall of</hi> BABYLON; which cannot poſſibly be meant but of <hi>material</hi> places and perdition on earth. In the nineteenth Chapter of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> in the firſt ſix verſes, we have five times HALLELU-JAH, and once PRAISE, <hi>to the Lord God omnipotent.</hi> By <hi>whom?</hi> Anſw. By <hi>the Hoſt</hi> or <hi>Camp of the four animals and four and twenty elders,</hi> called ſeveral times
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114976:10"/>
               <hi>much people.</hi> For <hi>what?</hi> Anſwer, <hi>For judging the Whore, and avenging the blood of the Saints on her. How?</hi> Anſwer, <hi>By caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Beaſt and the falſe prophet into the lake of fire; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying their Army by the ſword, ſo that the Fowles were filled with their fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which how it can be underſtood of meer <hi>Spiritualls,</hi> let them deviſe that are contrary minded; for I and others of greater learning cannot.<note place="margin">Mede, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>I need ſay no more for confirmation of the Doctrine. For <hi>Explication,</hi> I have already ſomthing anticipated my ſelf afore; <hi>viz.</hi> That Gods ſpeciall <hi>honouring</hi> the <hi>Saints</hi> with <hi>victories over their enemies,</hi> and the Saints reciprocally ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring God with <hi>praiſe</hi> for the ſame, <hi>relate mainly to our times and downward.</hi> For my part, I have delivered to you not any <hi>new notion,</hi> as <hi>new</hi> to <hi>me,</hi> as if formed by late <hi>ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes,</hi> but that I have been <hi>ſettled in</hi> for theſe eight yeares laſt paſt, at leaſt; and did not for bear to give a little notice of it in publique, when there was no great ſafety for one to utter ſuch things. I have for about ſo long foreſeen by the Word of God, that 1650. or thereabouts, would be a time full of great and glorious wonders.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Post Mille &amp; ſexcentos quirquageſimus annus</l>
               <l>Omnibus elapſis dignior annus erit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That which guided me to this expectation, were three places of ſcripture. The firſt Scripture, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. <hi>Daniel</hi> hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the wonderfull <hi>times of Michaels beginning to deliver his people, ver.</hi> 1, 2, 3. wherein, after great <hi>difficulties,</hi> the Saints ſhall begin to be ſo glorious upon the earth, (for that in the ſecond <hi>verſe</hi> cannot be meant of the laſt general reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, becauſe it mentions onely the riſing of SOME, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of <hi>Converting men,</hi> the queſtion is put, <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>How long ſhould it be to the end of thoſe wonders?</hi> The anſwer is, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. <hi>for a time, and times, and half a time;</hi> that is, for three ages and an
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114976:10"/>half, that is, 100. 200. and 50. in all, 350. Which computed according to the moſt learned, with the time that the <hi>Turk</hi> became the greateſt peſt and miſery to the Jewes, in or about the year 1300. the end of the reckoning falls upon 1650.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Scripture is in the 11. <hi>ver.</hi> of that 12 of <hi>Dan.</hi> where <hi>Daniel</hi> not ſatisfied with the former anſwer, askes a further explanation, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. The anſwer is given, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>From the time that the daily ſacrifice ſhall be taken away, there ſhall be one thouſand two hundred and ninety dayes</hi> (that is <hi>yeares</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4.4, 5, 6. where 390 and 40 dayes ſignifie ſo many years. <hi>I have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed thee each day for a year.</hi>
               </note>, as is the common phraſe of the Prophets; otherwiſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be made of it, to comfort <hi>Daniel,</hi> or the <hi>people of God,</hi> either <hi>Iewes</hi> or <hi>Gentiles.</hi>) Now the ceaſing of the <hi>Iewiſh daily ſacrifice</hi> was accompliſhed with ſo many viſible foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtsps and degrees, and with ſuch eminent note in the moſt famous Hiſtories, as the thing cannot poſſibly be hid from our eyes. Firſt, Upon ſome riſing of the Jewes againſt the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, <hi>Titus</hi> ſon to <hi>Veſpatian,</hi> Emperour, came and deſtroyed their Temple, about ſeventy yeares after Chriſt, according to Chriſts Propheſie, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.1, 2. Then the in <hi>daily ſacrifices</hi> ceaſed in the <hi>Temple:</hi> ſo that the Jews, yet zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of their ſacrifices, after that ſacrificed in the <hi>City,</hi> likely as ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r the remaining ruines of the <hi>Temple</hi> as they could. But upon ſome revolt of the Jewes from the Roman Empire, <hi>Adrian</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour came in his time, and about the year 134 after Chriſt, demoliſhed the <hi>City;</hi> whereby the <hi>daily ſacrifice</hi> was alſo <hi>taken away</hi> from the <hi>City;</hi> and by the Jewes was carried away to <hi>Mamre,</hi> where of old God appeared unto Abraham: There they build an Altar and ſacrifice, and force Merchants alſo to ſacrifice, or elſe inhibited their trade. Which <hi>Chriſtian Conſtantine the great,</hi> coming to the Empire with conqueſt of his heathen Colleagues, about the year 313, being not able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114976:11"/>beat down their <hi>Altar,</hi> and built there a publique place or <hi>Church</hi> (as the common phraſe is) for <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to worſhip God in. Then the Jews, driven to their laſt ſhiſt, return to reedifie Hieruſalem. By this time <hi>Inlian</hi> is Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and had ere long obtained his other name of <hi>Apoſtata,</hi> for revolting from the Chriſtian Religion, which a while he had profeſſed; who in defiance of Chriſt and the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion, encouraged the Jews to rebuild their Temple, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But fire and tempeſt from Heaven deſtroying their work, burning their tools, and hurting and terlifying the workmen, the Jewes never ſacrificed more. Now all know, that know any thing of <hi>Hiſtory</hi> or <hi>Chronologie,</hi> that <hi>Inlian</hi> came to be Emperour near about three hundred and ſixty years after Chriſt; and ſoon after, ſo encouraged the Jewes to that their ruine. Adde now three hundred and ſixty to one thouſand two hundred and ninety, and there is made up one thouſand ſix hundred and fifty.</p>
            <p>The third Scripture is in <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.5. <hi>To the Beaſt was given to DO and to ACT,</hi> (ſo in the Greek. See alſo the Margin of your Bible, and <hi>Brightman</hi>) I ſay, to <hi>DO and ACT,</hi> that is, <hi>to ſome purpoſe,</hi> for fourty two <hi>Moneths,</hi> (that is, ſolary moneths, thirty dayes to a moneth) that is, one thouſand two hundred and ſixty dayes; for ſo one thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſixty dayes, and fourty two months, are, and ſo are reckoned as all one, <hi>Rivel.</hi> 11.2, 3. Which one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand two hundred and ſixty days, are ſo many yeers, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Prophetical manner of ſpeech; as we may ſee by the effects, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>woman fleeing into the wilderneſs</hi> ſo long, and the <hi>Witneſſes propheſying in ſackcloth</hi> ſo long, Chap. 11. and Chap. 12. Now the firſt appearance of Antichriſt to be paſt a childe,<note place="margin">Vide <hi>Eliam Reuſnerum</hi> Iſug. Hiſt. in infant. Antich.</note> and to begin to <hi>work</hi> and <hi>act</hi> vigorouſly, was about the yeer 390 after Chriſt, wicked <hi>Arrianiſm,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the Godhead of Chriſt, then about increaſing, with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114976:11"/>many other ſymptomes of Antichriſt. Adde now 1260 to 390, and thence ariſeth 1650.</p>
            <p>If any do object, they do not yet ſee in this year 1650, the events to anſwer to the time: I ſhall onely ſay this, which I did at the beginning, that <hi>then about</hi> I expected great things. And whether then about, already, hath not been done great things, the binding of a King, and ſome Nobles; the change of Kingdoms into Common-wealths, the beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> over and over; our Fleet, a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to other Nations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> beſides Forrein tranſactions; I leave wiſe men to conſider. And what may be by the end of 1650, who can now foretell? But if no more ſhould come to paſſe, <hi>Exactly,</hi> within the compaſs of <hi>this</hi> year 1650, remember theſe three things. Firſt, That the learned Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nologers, and Aſtronomers, do know, that by reaſon there is but one day Odds, between the end of one year, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the next; and that there are certain odde houres every year, beſide the three hundred ſixty and five; that it is a ſmall matter to miſcount a year or two, in Chronologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call computations. Secondly, That <hi>Inlians</hi> fact in common account, was ſomething after three hundred and ſixty, <hi>viz.</hi> in three hundred ſixty and three. And others reckon, that fourty two months, or one thouſand two hundred and ſixty days, did not begin, till <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.6.) was removed, about the year 400. Thirdly, That 'tis told us in <hi>Daniel, ch.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 12. That though great things may be done about the year 1650, or a year or two over: Yet the bleſſed time of all on earth, is not till 1335 after the daily ſacrifice; which is fourty five years beyond 1650. Others upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother account, make it about ten yeares ſhorter; <hi>viz.</hi> the ruine of all the open obſtinate enemies of God, to be down by 1685. Be patient and pious the while: Be ſure to be on Chriſts ſide, and of the Holy People.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:114976:12"/>
            <p>You ſee in the Doctrine,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> Gods goodneſs; and the Doctrine made good: now let us put it to good Uſe, to move us to praiſe God. Praiſe is a <hi>Spirituall</hi> duty. <hi>Neceſſity</hi> may make Carnall men <hi>More ſuo,</hi> after their faſhion, to <hi>pray;</hi> but onely <hi>ſpirituality,</hi> by the Spirit, makes men to <hi>praiſe.</hi> So far as men by grace are made <hi>angelical</hi> and <hi>ſeraphical,</hi> ſo far they are complexioned to praiſe. If we be <hi>ſpiritual</hi> in truth, if we be Gods <hi>holy people</hi> indeed, and ſincerity, though never ſo weakly, here is much in this Doctrine, to direct, and erect, and raiſe our ſpirits to praiſe God, like the day, and like our ſelves. For the whole Doctrine is as a Divine Conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a ſpiritual <hi>Pleìades,</hi> ſtrongly radiated upon by the ſun of the Text and Context: That is, <hi>every word</hi> in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, is a ſeveral Star, that hath his ſeveral beams and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences; giving life as well as light, to quicken us in this days deſigne of praiſe. And they are in number ſeven, in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture conſiderable.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Word is, God <hi>commands.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 His <hi>Saints</hi> or HOLY PEOPLE;</item>
               <item>3 To <hi>praiſe;</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 For his <hi>performance;</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 According to his <hi>promiſe;</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6 Of <hi>honouring</hi> them;</item>
               <item>7 With <hi>ſuch</hi> honour.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And this ſeventh comes ſeaſonably <hi>laſt,</hi> in the rere, as the <hi>entrance</hi> to our REST or SABBATISM, as the Apoſtle calls it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.9.<note n="*" place="margin">So the <hi>Greek,</hi> as we ſhewed afore. <hi>Selah</hi> ſo oft in the Pſalms, ſignifies to <hi>liſt up.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>All theſe, that we may ſing them with SELAH, that is, heighten our ecchoes of praiſe ſutably to the joyful ſound of this day, would be conſidered,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Typically</hi> (if I may ſo ſpeak;) I mean, in a <hi>general</hi> RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PRESENTATION of the <hi>ſyſteme</hi> and <hi>platform</hi> of holy praiſe.</item>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:114976:12"/>
                  <item>2. <hi>Antitypically,</hi> in a <hi>ſpeciall</hi> anſwetableneſſe of our CONDITION; ſet, tuned, and fitted, to the higheſt KEY of ſuch a <hi>Platform.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. TYPICALLY.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God <hi>Commands.</hi> And who may more, and better <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> then <hi>He?</hi> He gives all to us, and us to all<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 1 4, 5. Gen. 1.1 <hi>omnibus p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia irre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſtentiae.</hi>
               </note>; and hath onely our praiſe for all. He Commands in the <hi>Old Creation,</hi> and all things obey: What <hi>men</hi> then, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of the <hi>New</hi> can diſobey. 'Tis not a <hi>Caſe of Conſcience,</hi> whether we may praiſe; but Gods <hi>Command to Conſcience, In every thing to give thankes,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.18. Intimaring, that in <hi>every thing,</hi> there is <hi>ſomething,</hi> that is a juſt reaſon of praiſe. And our righteous <hi>Maſter</hi> that bids us make <hi>Bricks,</hi> findes us <hi>Straw.</hi> No <hi>Precept</hi> is without a <hi>Promiſe.</hi> He hath ſaid, <hi>he will give, and poure out his ſpirit of grace and prayer</hi> into our hearts; that enables us to pray and prayſe, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 Yea, Gods very <hi>Command</hi> is vigorious, under the Goſpel, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. It doth not onely <hi>drive,</hi> but <hi>draw.</hi> God will concurre with his own Command, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Go, and I am with you,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo in other things, as Saints experience can teſtifie; who find that in prayſing, they riſe in prayſe. As <hi>Luther</hi> ſayd, <hi>Prayer is the beſt preparation to prayer.</hi> When we are warm in our Spirituall GEERES, we draw ſtrongeſt. Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure (ſayth the profound <hi>Philoſopher</hi>) the more 'tis acted, the more 'tis increaſed. Grace is the moſt active created thing under Heaven; and Prayſe in a gratious heart, the moſt ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denneſt thing to take fire. If David begin a <hi>Pſalm of prayſe</hi> in <hi>Gammut,</hi> he uſually ends in <hi>Ela.</hi> He mainly thrives in that, and aſcends above himſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His <hi>Holy-people,</hi> or Saints, or <hi>Holy-ones.</hi> This word is a word
Of Diſtinction, Of Obligation, Of Notion, or formal Conſideration.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:114976:13"/>
            <p n="1">1. Of <hi>Diſtinction. Holy-people</hi> are the proper perſons for prayſe. Theſe are the Spirituall <hi>Choriſters.</hi> The Apoſtle conjoynes theſe, as inſeparable, <hi>unthankfull, unholy.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore on the contrary,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.2.</note> theſe are inſeparable; <hi>Holy ones,</hi> are <hi>thankfull ones.</hi> The Heathen ſaw ſo much of this, as to ſay, <hi>Ingratum dixeris, &amp; omnia diexris:</hi> Say a man is unthankful, and ſay he is any thing. 'Tis a paunch of vices. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the Canon of contraries, Thankfullneſs is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of many Vertues. The beſt Spirits, are moſt prayſefull; prayſe being the common work of <hi>Angels, Luke</hi> 2. and the acclamations of the <hi>Seraphims, Iſai.</hi> 5. To whoſe pattrn we are to conform, as is hinted to us in the Lords prayer.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat. 6.10.</hi> Thy will be done on earth as tis in Heaven.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> the <hi>Saint</hi> that above all others, hath the ſtile of being <hi>a man after Gods own heart,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.14. is called the <hi>ſweet Pſalmiſt of Iſrael,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.1. And was the maine Author of the book of Pſalmes; which in the Hebrew, as we ſayd, are called <hi>Prayſes.</hi> And therefore men cannot (I ſhould think) refuſe to prayſe out of <hi>much</hi> Conſcience, but by reaſon of a defect in Conſcience.
<list>
                  <item>1. As if the Conſcience be either a <hi>dark Conſcience,</hi> which ſeekes light onely of the Hemiſphere of Night-ſtarrs, and of the ſame elevation and magnitude with it ſelf; not of morning-ſtarrs, which promiſe more light in the caſe that is put.</item>
                  <item>2. Or a <hi>made Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience;</hi> not native and genuine, but formed by borrowed debates, agreement, and example of others.</item>
                  <item>3. Or an <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged Conſcience;</hi> praiſe not conſiſting with its intereſt and deſigne.</item>
                  <item>4. Or an <hi>ill principled Conſcience;</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> that diſownes the <hi>Commanders</hi> as well as the <hi>Command</hi> of prayſe: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot ſpeak the language of prayſe in <hi>Scotiſh,</hi> or <hi>Iriſh.</hi> Surely with much ſorrow we may ſpeak it, that if it be poſſible that ſome <hi>Saints</hi> cannot ſee the <hi>leaſt</hi> cauſe to praiſe, in <hi>great</hi> deliverances, they are Saints under <hi>great temptations,</hi> and not with a <hi>little</hi> offence given to the generality of Saints.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114976:13"/>The <hi>tongue</hi> of a holy man is called his <hi>Glory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.9.</note> becauſe as 'tis the glory of members, ſo <hi>more</hi> in the mouthes of Saints, and moſt, in the act of prayſe. A <hi>Non-prayſing Saint,</hi> to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Divine reaſon, are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a contradiction in the adject, whiles ſuch. For <hi>Saint,</hi> or <hi>Holy people,</hi> is,</p>
            <p n="2">2. A word of <hi>Obligation.</hi> Saints or <hi>Holy-people</hi> ſignifies that ſuch are bound over by grace, to the duty of praiſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 30.4. Pſal. 52.9. Pſal. 89.5.132. 9, 16. Pſal. 145.10. Pſal. 33.1. Pſal 118.1, 2, 3.</note> becauſe holy. Therfore the Pſalmiſt oft ſets them this ditty and ſong; <hi>Sing unto the Lord,</hi> O YE SAINTS OF HIS. <hi>Prayſe is good before thy</hi> SAINTS. <hi>Thy faithfulneſſe ſhall be prayſed in the Congregatìon of</hi> SAINTS. <hi>Let thy SAINTS ſhout for joy.</hi> Saints ſhall ſhout aloud for joy. <hi>Thy SAINTS ſhall bleſſe thee.</hi> Prayſe is comely for the UPRIGHT. <hi>Praiſe the Lord, O YE SERVANTS of the Lord. O give thankes unto the Lord, for he is good: for his mercy endureth for ever. Let ISRAEL now ſay, that his mercy endureth for ever. Let the houſe of AARON now ſay, that his mercy endureth for ever. Let them that FEARE the Lord ſay, that his mercy endureth for ever.</hi> If Gods <hi>people</hi> praiſe, the holy <hi>Miniſtry</hi> muſt not be divided from them in that duty. Wee heard afore, that when the four Brigades of the <hi>Camp</hi> of God (in <hi>Revel.</hi>) prayſed, the <hi>four and twenty El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> did alſo. Saints have, as more divine reaſon <hi>wherefore,</hi> ſo more <hi>wherewith</hi> to prayſe. Holyneſſe implies that Saints are partakers of a holy God, in and through an holy Chriſt, by holy grace; and ſo are partakers of <hi>all,</hi> and of <hi>him</hi> that is <hi>more then all,</hi> Rom. 8.32.1 Cor. 3. the three laſt verſes. So that all, yea all <hi>adverſe</hi> things, <hi>work together for their good,</hi> Rom. 8. well therefore might the Apoſtle ſay, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. <hi>In</hi> EVERY <hi>thing give thankes.</hi> But if two Armies meet in the field, upon the Caſe of Nationall wrongs, the wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doer refuſeth to make ſatisfaction when deſired; they are both reſolved to try it out by the ſword; to Conquer, or be Conquered, (no middle of participation between:) the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114976:14"/>
               <hi>wronged</hi> party is ſet upon by the <hi>wrong-doer,</hi> once, againe, and a third time; the <hi>wronged</hi> party ſtill beating them, to at laſt a total rout, and full victory; can any gratious heart chuſe but ſee the <hi>the righteous hand of God</hi> in this againſt the wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doer? Can any Engliſh man, having any true Engliſh blood running in his Veines, chooſe but prayſe God for this delivernnce of the Nation? Surely the caſe thus put truely, as 'twas by the two Armies then reſolved, to win all or looſe all, we muſt either ſay, it was a mercy that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> conquered, or elſe it had been a mercy if <hi>Scotland</hi> had conquered. And if any were of that monſtrous minde, they might have conſidered, that they might have bequea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed good will and kindneſs to the <hi>Scots</hi> at a cheaper rate, then to ſet their own houſes on fire, to roſt their neighbours egges; that is, to looſe the <hi>Engliſh nation,</hi> to pleaſure the <hi>Scotiſh.</hi> But of this more anon; though I even faint to think on ſome among us, not the worſt of men; <hi>Quibus non ſuaſeris, etiamſi perſuaſeris;</hi> who though they are convicted, yet will not be converted in their opinions and judgment touching this thing. Saint, <hi>Redeas ad teipſum,</hi> return to thy ſelf, and to thy duty. If thou art a <hi>Saint,</hi> thou haſt all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and mercies of prayſe. Yea, all <hi>things</hi> to thee are <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies;</hi> upon every thing thou haſt, 'tis written, as upon a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veut mans houſe in every corner, <hi>Ergo landes,</hi> therefore praiſe. If Saints have <hi>perſonall</hi> mercies, none ſo injoys them as he. A <hi>Stranger</hi> (ſayth Solomon) <hi>intermeddles not with his joy.</hi> And <hi>his name</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Iohn</hi>) in his <hi>white ſtone, none knowes but he.</hi> If <hi>Oeconomicall</hi> mercies; The fire-ſtickes and fuell of comfort is layd cloſer together, to ſet his joy on flame, then others. If <hi>Nationall,</hi> none ſhares in ſuch mereies, ſo much as the <hi>Saints.</hi> The preſervation of this nation, is the preſervation of their choyſe delights, namely, <hi>piety and liberty;</hi> which the <hi>Almoſt-Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Semi-reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:114976:14"/>ſlaviſh ſpirits deem not. Therefore if ſome mens ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits be diſcompoſed to prayſe, ſhall the generality of <hi>Saints</hi> be uncompoſed? If miſcomplexioned mindes, not pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing the <hi>Donation,</hi> prayſe not the <hi>Donor,</hi> ſhall not the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chore of Holy people ſing, and ſay, <hi>Hallelujah, prayſed be Iehovah,</hi> the Army is ſafe, and the <hi>Parliament ſits,</hi> our <hi>Nation</hi> is in peace, this <hi>City</hi> in proſperity, <hi>Religion</hi> is preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and our <hi>Liberty</hi> ſecure? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.1, 2. <hi>O give thankes unto the Lord, for he is good, for his mercy endureth for ever: Let the redeemed of the Lord ſay ſo, whom he hath REDEEMED from the HAND of the enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Caſe of <hi>Deborahs</hi> prayſing, when other Tribes would not.</note> 
               <hi>Deborah</hi> and her Army of <hi>holy people,</hi> namely, the Tribes of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> of <hi>Zebulon,</hi> of <hi>Naphthali,</hi> and <hi>Iſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char,</hi> will fight; and conquering, will praiſe, (<hi>Judg.</hi> 5.) though the Tribe of <hi>Reuben be divided</hi> in his ſpirit and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, <hi>abiding among the ſheepfolds; Gilead is beyond Jordan, Dan is in ſhips, Aſher is on the ſea-ſhore.</hi> See, here is wicked <hi>tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Jabin and Siſera,</hi> as bad enemies to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as the <hi>Iriſh rebels</hi> to us; yet the laſt-named Tribes will neither fight nor praiſe. Therefore in this Chapter, where their part ſhould come in, there is (as we ſay in Muſick) a <hi>Large-Reſt:</hi> They ſing not; keep not tune nor time. Yea, their part is ſmeared with a blot upon record, by God himſelf, to diſgrace their evil deed to this day.<note place="margin">The Caſe of <hi>David,</hi> mourning over that Victory of which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were glad.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But there is a greater wonder then this, of <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 18, &amp;c. that when the danger was neer, even in the bowels of the Kingdom of <hi>David,</hi> and the foundation of the Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection was laid in the hearts of the moſt of his own Subjects, headed by his own leud ſon, likely to pull the Crown from his fathers head, who now with his petty Army is fain to flee from his own Throne; yet upon the obtaining of a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Victory againſt that Arch-rebel and Rebellion, <hi>David</hi> is ſo far diſtempered in ſpirit, that he mourns over the <hi>matter</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:114976:15"/>and <hi>means</hi> of his deliverance; and, not unlike ſome others, would comply<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> 2 Sam. 19.2.</note> (as the manner is) with a King or at leaſt frown upon them that wrought the deliverance. But <hi>Joab</hi> and his Army were glad; as they had good cauſe. You will ſay, Can ye blame <hi>David? Abſalom,</hi> that was ſlain, was his ſon. And ſome of <hi>Davids</hi> BRETHREN fell in Battel with him. Was he? The Rebellion was the more horrid, the danger far the greater, if <hi>Abſalom</hi> had prevailed: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the merciful deliverance was of the ſame ſize; and ſhould have been the meaſure of <hi>Davids</hi> joy. And to our buſineſs, the Objection is our advantage. <hi>Abſalom</hi> was his ſon, and that was neerer kin to <hi>David,</hi> then any <hi>King</hi> to us. And they that were beaten in Battel, were <hi>Brethren;</hi> and therefore neerer allied to <hi>David Joab,</hi> and to the conquering army, in Notion and Nation, in form of Worſhip, union of <hi>Policy,</hi> Blood, Territories, and Temple, then the <hi>Scots</hi> are to us: yet for all this, 'twas <hi>Davids</hi> failing, his great fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to mourn over <hi>Abſaloms</hi> death,<note place="margin">See D. <hi>Har.</hi> in Abſal. funeral.</note> and his armies downfal.. So learned and godly <hi>Divines</hi> urge the ſtory, for the proof of Saints weakneſſes: and unto that form and ſhape the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſtory moſt emphatically limbs it out to the life. And <hi>Joabs</hi> wiſe carriage on the contrary part (Chap. 19.) is as ſingularly pourtrayed, his honour emblazoned, and he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatorily deſcribed, for rounding the King to purpoſe for his indiſcretion.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.5, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ioab</hi> to <hi>David</hi>) <hi>ſhamed the faces of all thy ſervants this day, which this day have ſaved thy</hi> LIFE, <hi>and the lives of thy ſons, and of thy daughters, and the lives of thy wives,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in that thou</hi> LOVES <hi>thine</hi> ENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIES, <hi>and</hi> HATEST <hi>thy</hi> FRIENDS: <hi>for thou hast decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this day, that thou regardeſt neither Princes, nor ſervants: for this day I perceive that if. Abſalom had lived, and all we had died this day, then it bad pleaſed thee well. Now therefore ariſe go forth, and ſpeak comfortably</hi> (Heb. <hi>to the heart</hi>) <hi>to thy ſervants,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114976:15"/>(A notable ſpeech, and looks keenly, with a piercing eye, on ſome that now mourn for our Victory, and worſe then <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> who did it in his private chamber, but they in their publike prayers.) With this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouzing, home, and juſt Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>David</hi> is convinced of his folly: he <hi>ariſeth,</hi> yea, and <hi>goes and ſits in the gate;</hi> to incourage and comfort the people, for winning that victory. Now therefore, was it not well done of <hi>Joab,</hi> and his <hi>Army,</hi> to rejoyce in the victory; though the <hi>King</hi> was the head and chiefe of them, that would have turned it into a day of mourning? But is there no regard to be had, to the ſlaughter of <hi>Brethren,</hi> and ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>blood;</hi> for which <hi>Iſrael</hi> mourned in the Caſe of <hi>Benjamin, Judg.</hi> 21? Marke it, once for all, we rejoyce not at all, in the <hi>ſhedding of blood,</hi> preciſely conſidered as <hi>ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of blood;</hi> much leſs in the ſhedding of the blood of <hi>Brethren.</hi> But that the wronged Engliſh party, (as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Declarations of the Parliament have demonſtrated) do rather Conquer, then are Conquered; therein we juſtly rejoyce, and praiſe God for it, though (becauſe it could not be avoided) it coſt blood, and the blood of Brethren;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Benjamins</hi> Caſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed, touching the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning after their over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw. So in <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilions</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion, and in the relations of it in print, and from other good teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</note> as in the Caſe of <hi>Abſalom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Caſe of <hi>Benjamin;</hi> we will refer our Caſe to that, to be tryed. It ſures to our condition, and is exceeding much for us. The ſtory is in the 19, 20, 21, <hi>Chapters</hi> of <hi>Judges,</hi> I need not relate it but onely apply it. The cauſe of the other Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> warring againſt that of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> was far leſs then ours againſt the <hi>Scots.</hi> Ours was, their pub-like invaſion of our Country, with a mighty Army; (by authority of the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi>) waſting a part of our Nation; killing ſome of our men, occaſioning the death of others; taking away our children captives, making their parents to redeem their own children with money, and ſome more then once; undoing many families with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114976:16"/>taxes; plundering men of their goods, and cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; calling our land <hi>Scotland,</hi> as they further invaded us; threatning death to them that contradicted them therein. And ſince that, they have proclaimed a King, over this Nation of <hi>England,</hi> contrary to the Declaration of our Parliament. And for all this, have refuſed to give in any ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. But the cauſe of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> war againſt <hi>Benjamin,</hi> was but <hi>perſonal,</hi> ſome vile fellowes of <hi>Gibea</hi> raviſhing the <hi>Levites</hi> Concubine to death; that town and the reſt of the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin</hi> refuſing to give ſatisfaction, in delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up the malefactors, though <hi>Iſrael</hi> were warned, and wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed thereunto; that ſo guilt might not lie upon the land. Yet for this cauſe, (inferior to ours) the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> make warre upon the <hi>Benjamites;</hi> farre nearer brethren to them, then the <hi>Scots</hi> to us. Therefore thus farre, no cauſe of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or <hi>us;</hi> a good cauſe, is no cauſe of ſorrow. In proſecution whereof, <hi>Iſrael</hi> asked counſel of God, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times (as did we): they were bid by <hi>Oracle</hi> ſeveral times to go, as we were by many <hi>clear impreſsions</hi> upon our Spirits, upon ſolemn daies of Humiliation,<note place="margin">So it was impreſſed upon the hearts of the <hi>Army,</hi> and of the <hi>Churches</hi> in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; as they gave in their accounts, after the dayes of Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> kept for that end, to know the minde of God. So that nor yet, was there any cauſe of ſorrow, to us or them. The ultimate event of the totall overthrow of the Army of the <hi>Benjamites,</hi> ſealed it to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that God was with them; as the ſame ſeal was given to us, in the totall rout of the <hi>Scotiſh Army.</hi> And in this alſo, preciſely conſidered, as Gods <hi>anſwer of prayer,</hi> his <hi>performance</hi> of his <hi>own Counſel,</hi> the <hi>manifeſtation of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> with the innocent, with <hi>puniſhment upon the wrong-doer;</hi> there is found no cauſe of ſorrow for either of us. But in the <hi>middle tranſactions</hi> did <hi>Iſrael</hi> fall in battle twice (for ſome ſecret ſin, as they did at <hi>Ai</hi>) we (ever bleſſed be <hi>Jehovah</hi>) fell not at all before the <hi>Scots.</hi> Therefore the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> might well mourn more, and have leſs cauſe of rejoycing then
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114976:16"/>we. But mark by the way, for all the <hi>Notion</hi> of <hi>Brethren,</hi> the <hi>Benjamites</hi> mourn not for the fall of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> that we read of. 'Tis juſt as if now, the <hi>contrary minded</hi> among us, ſhould mourn for the overthrow of the <hi>Scots,</hi> becauſe (as they cry) they are their <hi>Brethren:</hi> but they never mourn for them few that were killed of <hi>us,</hi> or for our diſtreſſes by weather, or want of proviſion, for the whole army, or for the diſtreſſes and wounds of many of us; as if we were not Brethren to them. <hi>Benjamin</hi> will not mourn for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> though in two battles they kill of Iſrael <hi>fourty thouſand men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 20.</note> If <hi>Iſrael</hi> will, they may at laſt mourn <hi>gratis,</hi> for <hi>Benjamin,</hi> and the mean while for themſelves, for their twice falling before <hi>Benjamin, Benjamin</hi> regards it not: whence I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that if the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had conquered the <hi>Benjamites</hi> at thoſe times, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> would have ſaved their mourning, and would have been glad of conqueſt: For they are in the caſe, immediate contraries. 'Tis true, that afterwards that the moſt part of the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin</hi> were cut off, and the whole Tribe even extinct, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> mourn. But the formal conſideration, and preciſe reaſon would be weighed, and heeded; eſpecially by men, that moſt pretend to moſt reaſon. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> cannot mourn for ſtanding up for a moſt <hi>righteous cauſe;</hi> nor for <hi>Conquering</hi> the <hi>Benjamites;</hi> to which God encouraged them by three ſeverall anſwers, <hi>bidding them go.</hi> What then? 'Tis upon another account.
<list>
                  <item>1. A <hi>Tribe</hi> was cut off. The diſtinction of Tribes being then much preſerved, to diſtinguiſh the comming of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> of the Tribe of Judah, as was fore-propheſied. Now this conſideration of Tribes, contributs nothing to our caſe, to cauſe us to mourn, or hinder our joy for our victory over the <hi>Socts.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. And mainly, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> mourned for their Raſh COVENANT. Which they choſeing rather, to break then keep, they were pacified<note place="margin">Judg. 21.</note>
                  </item>
               </list> But the Iſrael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114976:17"/>were ſo farre from mourning, for the <hi>ſlaughter</hi> of the <hi>Benjamites,</hi> that now after all, they ſend twelve thouſand men againſt <hi>Iabeſh-Gilead</hi> to deſtroy it, and in it all, both man and woman, that had layn with man, for that they came not up to help them to conquer <hi>Benjamin</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Judg. 21.</note>. If poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly men may be convinced, this would, if weighed, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convince them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But there was no <hi>ſolemn thanker</hi> for theſe victories againſt <hi>Brethren.</hi> Anſwer, Thoſe that make this Objection, can tell us if they pleaſe, that extraordinary duties, and daies, as of <hi>Faſting</hi> and <hi>Feaſting,</hi> or <hi>Praying</hi> and <hi>Praiſing,</hi> are to be taken up by the people of God, <hi>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>renatâ,</hi> occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, as ſome extraordinary cauſe is offered by divine Providence. So that we are not tyed to <hi>rules</hi> or <hi>example,</hi> when to ſet ſuch times apart, but as God acts for, and makes impreſſions upon, the hearts of his people. But if this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer will not ſerve their turnes, we adde; that though <hi>David</hi> blubbred for the overthrow of <hi>Abſalom,</hi> as we heard afore. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. yet after, he was not onely <hi>Convinced, Chap.</hi> 19. as hath been declared, but in the 22 <hi>Chap.</hi> hath a <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn pſalm of praiſe,</hi> for his deliverance from <hi>all his enemies;</hi> (in which <hi>Abſalom</hi> muſt needs be included) from the <hi>firſt</hi> oppoſition of <hi>Saul,</hi> down to <hi>that</hi> day, as the <hi>Title</hi> of the <hi>Pſalm</hi> (Canonical Scripture as well as the reſt) hath it. And is twice upon record, <hi>v. z.</hi> there, and the 18. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> left for all <hi>Iſrael to ſing,</hi> and <hi>praiſe God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to leave diſputes, the truth is, the greateſt Core and cauſe of non-praiſing God, is, <hi>the corruption of mans heart;</hi> if the heart be out of tune, it will not praiſe, be the cauſe (almoſt) what it will;<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.18.</note> though the <hi>Holy people</hi> are bound, and obey, <hi>In every thing to give thankes;</hi> much <hi>more</hi> in greater mercies. We have a renowned inſtance of both, in <hi>Ezra</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 10. to the end of the Chapter. One could not but
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114976:17"/>thinke (had not the event ſhewed the contrary) that <hi>all the Iewes</hi> would have <hi>praiſed God</hi> at the laying of the <hi>foundati on of their ſecond Temple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Caſe</hi> of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound of ſorrow and joy, at the laying of the <hi>foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the <hi>Temple.</hi>
               </note> after their return from the <hi>Babylont an</hi> Captivitie; and with an <hi>heigth of joy,</hi> anſwerable to the <hi>depth of ſorrow</hi> they had been in, for the <hi>ruine of the firſt,</hi> and their long <hi>inſlavement there</hi> But lo, in ſtead thereof, a many <hi>Mal-contents, howle and mourn,</hi> while others <hi>joy.</hi> A confuſion to be wondred at; which will more appear, and ſerve this day, if we do but ſhew you barely the roots of ten remarkable obſervations, natively growing there; which tranſplanted, by your ſelves into your own hearts, will ſpring up to a great talneſs, by a little meditation. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Namely, That the beginnings of reformation, are times of great <hi>diſcrimination,</hi> of the complexions of mens Spirits. In this Third of <hi>Ezra,</hi> 10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon the ſaid occaſion, <hi>Iew</hi> is diſtinguiſhed from <hi>Iew.</hi> They are not all of one mind, ſome take <hi>content,</hi> ſome <hi>diſcontent,</hi> in, and about the ſame thing. They are all fire-brands, but newly taken out of the fire; ſome flame with joy, but others quencht and hiſſe with teares of ſorrow. In ſuch times of reforming, will ariſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> counter-<hi>actings,</hi> contrary <hi>tranſactions.</hi> For the ſelf-ſame thing, ſome here <hi>ſing and praiſe,</hi> others <hi>weep with a loud voyce.</hi> In the like times, the <hi>afflicted</hi> endeavour to o're<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>top, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> drown, and ſwallow up, the actions of the <hi>well-affected,</hi> with their peremptory counter-actings; the <hi>cryings of the lamenters, almoſt overcome, and confound the ſhoutings of the rejoycers.</hi> Of thoſe that are ſo <hi>ill-affected</hi> there, are <hi>Miniſters,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and ancient <hi>Profeſſors:</hi> (Neither <hi>learning</hi> nor <hi>experience,</hi> without the help of grace, are able to act graciouſly) and they are the men (chiefly) that conterpoiſe againſt the <hi>well-effected,</hi> both of <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> in the ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of that dayes praiſe. For the Text is expreſs; <hi>And when the builders layd the foundation of the Temple of the Lord,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114976:18"/>they ſet the</hi> PRIESTS <hi>in their apparell with Trumpets, and the</hi> LEVITES <hi>the ſonnes of Aſaph with Cymhals, to</hi> PRAISE <hi>the</hi> LORD, <hi>after the ordinance of David, King of Iſrael. And they ſang by courſe, in praiſing and giving thanks unto the Lord, becauſe he</hi> IS GOOD: FOR HIS MERCY ENDU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RETH FOR EVER. See with what <hi>manner</hi> of ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and high obſervation of the day, the <hi>Sweetly-compoſed</hi> Miniſters and People praiſe God. And obſerve with a judicious eye, what is the <hi>matter</hi> of their ſong and praiſe; even part of the 136 <hi>Pſal.</hi> as <hi>now</hi> further fulfilled, as <hi>before</hi> it was fulfilled in part, in their deliverance from <hi>Egypt,</hi> and their <hi>Conqueſts</hi> in the <hi>wilderneſs, &amp;c.</hi> and in <hi>Canaan;</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we diſputed, touching the <hi>typicalneſs</hi> of <hi>deliverances,</hi> and the <hi>ſucceſſive</hi> performance of <hi>promiſes.</hi> But how ſtands affected the other Miniſters and ancient Profeſſors? The Text tels you plainly. <hi>But</hi> MANY <hi>of the</hi> PREISTS <hi>and</hi> LEVITES, <hi>and chiefe of the</hi> FATHERS <hi>who were</hi> ANCI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ENT MEN, <hi>that had ſeen the firſt houſe; when the foundation of this houſe was layd afore their eyes,</hi> WEPT WITH A <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> LOUD VOICE. Theſe learned Miniſters and ancient Profeſſors, have alſo ſome ſhew of <hi>reaſon</hi> for their mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſome ſemblance <hi>of affection, and Zeale to the common good;</hi> namely, becauſe it did ſeem by the <hi>platform</hi> layd, their condition as in regard of magnificence, was like to be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> meaner ſomething, then formerly. This they thought, becauſe they <hi>carnally</hi> looked upon the <hi>outſide of things,</hi> and not to what ſpiritual glory God might caſt upon this <hi>ſecond</hi> (though leſſer) <hi>Temple,</hi> by ſending the <hi>Meſſias</hi> to preach in it. This <hi>Hag. chap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doth intimate. And further, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> they <hi>imprudently judged the utmoſt events of their preſent mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, by the ſmall beginnings of things.</hi> Becauſe the <hi>foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Temple</hi> was leſs, therefore they conclude, all things ſhould be, from time to time diminiſhed and leſſened; a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114976:18"/>moſt falſe ground of right judging, and determinations. Theſe <hi>Mal-contents</hi> doubt not but that <hi>preſently</hi> and <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> they may <hi>prudently</hi> enough declare their diſcontent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>publike and ſolemn day of joy and praiſe.</hi> By which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> and contrariety of their ſpirits, and manifeſted acts, much people are much amuſed, and amazed. So plainly this text of <hi>Ezra: The Prieſts, and Levites, and chief of the fathers</hi> (that wept) <hi>wept with aloud voice, and many ſhouted aloud for joy; ſo that the people could not diſcern the noiſe of the ſhout of joy, from the noiſe of the weeping of the</hi> PEOPLE. But, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> all theſe things to impede and prejudice this day of mercy and praiſe at the foundation of the Temple, God reſerves and raiſeth the hearts of a remnant, nay a great party, to praiſe; who are in this 3 of <hi>EZra,</hi> and <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.2. encouraged and commended, and the non-praiſers diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced there upon record. We ſee by this, that whiles men are miſtaken in their judgements, and diſtempered in their ſpirits, a <hi>great matter</hi> will not make them praiſe. But as it runs in the Head we are upon, the duty lies upon the <hi>HOLY</hi> PEOPLE. Which is not onely a word of <hi>diſtinction,</hi> and <hi>obligation,</hi> as we have heard, but,</p>
            <p n="3">3. A word of <hi>Notion,</hi> or <hi>Formal conſideration;</hi> under which the Saints muſt praiſe: Namely,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Spiritually</hi> conſidered as <hi>Holy.</hi> No <hi>diſtinction of Sects</hi> (as good men are oft reproached;) no <hi>variety of judgements</hi> in non-Fundamentals; no <hi>differences of forms of Diſcipline,</hi> that are not oppoſite to the Word of God; no <hi>diſcrimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Presbyteries and Congregations,</hi> ſo as they be all <hi>Saints, holy</hi> perſons, <hi>ſhould,</hi> much leſs <hi>ſhall</hi> (for future) come into conſideration, to hinder praiſe. All that are <hi>holy,</hi> do, muſt, ſhall, and will praiſe God for mercies. All that own <hi>Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> muſt own their God, own their mercies; and both in a day of praiſe, leſt they forfeit their <hi>recognizance</hi> of <hi>Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:114976:19"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Civilly</hi> conſidered as <hi>people;</hi> in oppoſite diſtinction to <hi>Kings: Monarchie</hi> being turned into <hi>Democracie; Kingdoms</hi> into <hi>Commonweals.</hi> My heart trembles to think of a <hi>popular parity;</hi> a <hi>levilling Anarchie,</hi> to which theſe times, to my terrour, much incline among the multitude Hiſtories, and ancient examples, warn us of ſuch, as an immediate preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation to ruine. But a regular <hi>Democracie</hi> aſſiſted with an occaſional <hi>Aristocracie</hi> in <hi>Trust,</hi> is moſt ſafe; as ſome expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience may be ſeen, in <hi>SwitZerland, Venice, Low-countries,</hi> and <hi>New-England;</hi> and moſt anciently among the <hi>Iews,</hi> in the time of the Judges; or ſomething afore, <hi>Moſes</hi> being but a <hi>Prophet</hi> to <hi>direct</hi> what was the minde and Laws of God: and <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> but their <hi>General,</hi> in caſe of <hi>War,</hi> as were after their <hi>Iudges.</hi> Under which notion onely were Kings choſen, whiles kept to their proper duty. Of <hi>degenerated Kings,</hi> of which, <hi>Iuſtin</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Arbitrium principis erat pro Legibus,</hi> the Will of the Prince was the Law; <hi>Nimrod</hi> was the firſt, we read of; whom the Scripture brands with the diſgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful title of a <hi>Mighty-Hunter,</hi> that is, a <hi>Man-Hunter,</hi> a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.8. The next were the nine <hi>Heathen</hi> Kings, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. whiles the holy people kept their Government within the bounds of Families, <hi>Ibid.</hi> in the ſame 14 Chapter of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis.</hi> And next to them, the <hi>Kings</hi> of wicked <hi>Edom,</hi> that is, <hi>Eſau,</hi> Gen. 36. The <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> after deſiring of a King, in the time of <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet, God is diſpleaſed at it, (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.5, 6, 7, 8.) and <hi>gave them a king in his wrath</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Hoſea, 13.11.</note>, who proved a great <hi>plague</hi> to them, as God fotetold them (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.) And after, how did moſt of the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> prove <hi>bad!</hi> and ſince Chriſt till now, what hath the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of them done for Chriſt? but much againſt Chriſt, and true Chriſtians: yea, and have been the grand oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the world, daſhing millions of men to pieces in bloody wars, to ſatiate the thirſt of their own ambition, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114976:19"/>enlargement of Dominions. No wonder therefore if the world in many ages have <hi>declined</hi> from <hi>Monarchie</hi> (as in the time of the <hi>Maechabees,</hi> and the <hi>Romane</hi> State) and inclined to a <hi>Democracie,</hi> as among the <hi>Athenians</hi> of old, and <hi>Helvetians</hi> of late, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Look narrowly unto it, and we ſhall finde that the loweſt foundation of the Government of <hi>England;</hi> and ſome monuments of its ſuperſtructure, teſtifie in the behalf of a <hi>Democracie</hi> amongſt us. What mean elſe, our <hi>Iuries</hi> in moſt <hi>Courts;</hi> our determining things by <hi>Vote,</hi> in other Courts, or aſſemblies of <hi>ſuffrage;</hi> our Repreſentatives in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; our choice of Burgeſſes of Towns, and Knights of the Shire, to ſit in Parliament; our <hi>conſent</hi> asked at the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation</hi> of our former Kings, <hi>Will you have this man to be your King?</hi> our receiving of him, with <hi>condition</hi> to <hi>rule ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Laws;</hi> our <hi>ſwearing</hi> him to that; our requiring him to paſs in Parliament all the Laws <hi>quas populus eligeret,</hi> that ſhould be agreed by our Repreſentatives in Parliament? Yea, before the <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> our Chronicles make mention of ſeveral Kings depoſed by the people of <hi>England, judicially;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stowes <hi>Chron. of</hi> Archigallo, Merianus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> ſome for drunkenneſs, and wickedneſs of life; others for laying too heavie Taxes on the Nation. And there is a Divine reaſon, above all, that Nations ſhould incline to a <hi>Democratical Government;</hi> becauſe God did not onely <hi>create us people,</hi> (not Kings) but alſo he hath <hi>ſetled his Decree</hi> againſt <hi>Monarchie,</hi> Dan. 2. where the <hi>Image of four metals</hi> of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> ('tis not ſaid of Antichriſt) ſhall be <hi>broken to pieces.</hi> Three are gone; the <hi>Aſſyrio-Chaldean,</hi> the <hi>Medo-Perſian,</hi> and the <hi>Grecian;</hi> the feet, legs, and toes of <hi>Iron</hi> and of <hi>Clay</hi> of the <hi>Romane,</hi> to be crumbled; and now comes on the tragical ſtage to that end. And all this to be done, to make way for <hi>Chriſts viſible kingdom</hi> on earth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14. compared with our <hi>Text,</hi> and the <hi>Revelations</hi> thorowout. <hi>Monarchie</hi> hath been extoll'd by <hi>Book-polititians,</hi> for <hi>Majeſtie,</hi> and likeneſs
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114976:20"/>to the rule of God: But it hath ſo long <hi>degenerated</hi> into <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancie</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> that it is now diſgracing it ſelf out of the world. <hi>Democracie</hi> hath been ſometimes <hi>deſpiſed,</hi> where and while it hath been eclipſed by the ſeeming-ſplendor of Lord-enſnaring and people-vaſſal ging <hi>Royalty.</hi> But what it wants in <hi>Majeſty,</hi> is richly made up in true <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>ſecure Safety.</hi> The people loving the Governmen of the People (as before deſcribed) love <hi>themſelves.</hi> But Kings loving themſelves, and their Court-creatures, they drained and ſuck'd out the life, and blood, and ſpirits of the State. The Peoples miſery and poverty (as was their <hi>Maxime</hi>) was their ſecurity to do what they liſt. The time is now at hand, to dethrone <hi>Monarchie,</hi> and to raiſe <hi>Democracie,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Text of the <hi>Honour to be given</hi> to the <hi>Holy-people,</hi> compared with <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.27. Read it wiſely. <hi>The</hi> KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOM <hi>and</hi> DOMINION, <hi>and the</hi> GREATNESSE <hi>of the Kingdom</hi> UNDER <hi>the</hi> WHOLE HEAVEN, <hi>ſhall be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the</hi> PEOPLE <hi>of the</hi> SAINTS. You ſee then, our Text, and that of <hi>Daniel,</hi> ſpeakes fairely for a <hi>Democracie,</hi> that is <hi>holy;</hi> and our Times, begin to ecchoe diſtinctly to it, as we ſhall ſee more after, in the <hi>Antitypicall</hi> conſideration of the termes of our Doctrine, and Text.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Word</hi> is, <hi>Praiſe</hi> ye the Lord; or, as 'tis in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, HALLELU-JAH, which is (as I may ſay) the Heavenly prick-ſong of the times ſignified in the <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> to our preſent time, and downward. When had we cauſe more to praiſe <hi>Jah</hi> or <hi>Jehovah,</hi> then now? When did he more manifeſt himſelf, as <hi>ſuch,</hi> then now, by that time we have reckoned up the many things of this daies memorial? And the <hi>duty</hi> is like the <hi>deſert.</hi> It doth not onely ſound of what we <hi>muſt</hi> do, but ſavours of much <hi>ſweetneſs in the doing;</hi> and ſo a <hi>motive</hi> as well as a <hi>Command</hi> to praiſe. For, Praiſe is a <hi>preparation to prayer.</hi> He that is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:114976:20"/>not in tune to pray, let him firſt play the <hi>praludium</hi> of praiſe, he ſhall ſoon finde his heart, before bed-ridden ſick ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, to come to his life and ſtrength. So it appeares by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Pſalmes often. For praiſe is a great <hi>heart-melter,</hi> a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincer <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of ſin, in regard of the unkindneſs of it; and ſo an admirer of divine mercy; as <hi>Jacob; Lord, I am leſſe then the leaſt of all thy mercies.</hi> For, Praiſe is an <hi>owning of the returnes</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>of our prayers.</hi> We know our prayers againe, when we ſee them acted and effected; and make us Eccho to God acts as <hi>David; Away from me ye workers of iniquity, the Lord hath heard me.</hi> (Pſal. 6) <hi>What ſhall I render to the Lord</hi> (Pſal. 116) <hi>for all his benefit?</hi> Therefore praiſe alſo, is a <hi>quieter of</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>diſcontent,</hi> a compoſer of our ſpirits, an allayer of the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinies of the affections, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77. It is the <hi>intent</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
               <hi>and event of Gods deliverances,</hi> and the acceptable glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> of him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 23. And tis a great <hi>tryer of the actions;</hi> that is in judgment and Conſcience well done, for which a Saint can cordially give praiſe. Therefore praiſe we for the <hi>thing done;</hi> for <hi>eyes</hi> to ſee cauſe of praiſe; and for <hi>hearts</hi> willing to give thankes; And whiles we praiſe, we looſe no time to procure at the Throne of Grace. Praiſe is as <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> well a <hi>potencie and prevayling to get,</hi> as a pledge, we have received. As well a <hi>Petition,</hi> as an accquittance. So in the ſtory of <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> who whiles he praiſed,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 20.22, &amp;c.</note> obtained the victory of an Army of enemies. Therefore doubt not but that this daies praiſe, ſhall have the fruit of Petitions. Therefore to all theſe ſeven, let the foot of the ſong be, <hi>Therefore praiſe, therefore praiſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Word</hi> is <hi>Performance,</hi> Pſal. 136.3, &amp;c. <hi>O give thankes unto the Lord of</hi> HOSTS, <hi>who alone doth</hi> GREAT WON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERS: <hi>for his mercy indures for ever,</hi> &amp;c. Who <hi>remembred us in our</hi> LOW ESTATE: <hi>for his mercy indureth for ever. And</hi> REDEEMED <hi>us from our</hi> ENEMIES: <hi>for his mercy indureth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114976:21"/>for ever.</hi> Need I ſpeak to this Text? The day is a plain and compleat commentary.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Word</hi> is, according to his <hi>Promiſe.</hi> Not onely great <hi>things</hi> are done for us, but with the great ſeale of Gods <hi>truth;</hi> that he <hi>heares,</hi> when we do <hi>pray;</hi> and <hi>doth</hi> as he <hi>ſpeaks.</hi> So that in what we have heard, and ſeen, and injoy, being the <hi>iſſue of promiſes,</hi> all is not done, till THIS world be done. Gods <hi>Promiſes</hi> are of an unknown <hi>worth,</hi> a rich <hi>improvement,</hi> and of endleſs incomes of <hi>Reverſions.</hi> Promiſes are like the ſunne, that caſts its beames at firſt riſing, from Eaſt to Weſt. Yea they are like to fountainous ſtreames, the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they runne, the more they are augmented, till they disburded themſelves into the Ocean. This is a great myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. I had the firſt hint of it many yeeres ſince from learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and religious <hi>Calvin.</hi> Promiſes have never an end of all in them, till Saints attaine the perfect end of all. So that as all the promiſes and performances of the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> did <hi>firſt</hi> devolve themſelves on the great period of <hi>Chriſts incarnation;</hi> ſo next they reach to, and reſt upon Chriſts <hi>exaltation of his Kingdome on earth</hi> among his Holy-people, as they are anewly promiſed or commented upon, in the <hi>New.</hi> Men may not yet ſay of the <hi>grand promiſes of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall good of the Holy-people,</hi> Now ſuch a promiſe is fullfilled, and now ſuch a promiſe is fullfilled; unleſs they mean <hi>fullfilled</hi> ſo as not yet <hi>fully fullfilled.</hi> What ever is done, till the full perfection of all things come, is but an <hi>Epocha, Intervall,</hi> or <hi>Stage</hi> of the progreſſe of promiſes; and their ſeverall <hi>Geſſes.</hi> Promiſes in their effectuall movings, are like the movings of the Sea, the latter wave is the greater, and the outwarder circle the wider. We now wonder at the greatneſs of mercies preſent. But he is immenſe that acts. Now, are but dawnings to the ſunne hereafter riſing, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. The <hi>Holy-people</hi> are now honoured; But ſhall
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:114976:21"/>be more, and more; So it followes in the two <hi>words</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, namely <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>ſuch</hi> honour; with addition to ALL his <hi>Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Word</hi> is <hi>honour.</hi> God will honour <hi>them,</hi> whom the world all along till now, have moſt <hi>vilified.</hi> He will make them glorious before men, whom (as <hi>Paul</hi> faith) men have made <hi>the off-ſcowring of all things.</hi> Now, it is not onely a matter of <hi>conſcience</hi> towards God, but of <hi>credit</hi> among men, to be a <hi>Saint.</hi> And ſhall not ſuch praiſe? Yea, they muſt, they do, they will. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9, &amp;c, <hi>The four Beaſts and the four and twenty Elders fell down before the Lamb,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And they ſung a NEW ſong, ſaying, Thou art worthy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for thou waſt ſtain, and haſt redeemed us,</hi> &amp;c: <hi>out of every nation, and haſt made us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our God Kings and Prieſts, and we ſhall REIGN on the EARTH. And I beheld, and heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beaſts, and the elders; and the number of them was ten thouſand times ten thouſand, and thouſands of thouſands, ſaying with a loud voice, Worthy is the Lamb that was ſlain, to receive POWER, and glory,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And every CREATURE in heaven, and ON THE EARTH,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>heard I, ſaying, Bleſsing, honour, glory, and power,</hi> &amp;c. Surely, if God will honour <hi>his people</hi> by glorious performances, they ſhall honour him with praiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.</p>
            <p n="7">7 And laſt <hi>word</hi> is, <hi>SUCH honour,</hi> namely, to <hi>ſubdue Kings, and Nobles, and Nations.</hi> If (as 'tis twice ſpoken, and almoſt together, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. to wit, verſ. 24. and v. 26.) <hi>The Kings and Nations ſhall</hi> ſo <hi>love the light and glory of Ieruſalem,</hi> (that is, of the <hi>holy people) to WALK in it, and bring their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory to it,</hi> well: If not, they all fall before and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my Text; The <hi>Holy people</hi> ſhall <hi>execute vengeance upon the Nations, and puniſhments upon the people: To binde their Kings with chains, and their Nobles with fetters of iron:</hi> THIS HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOUR HAVE ALL HIS SAINTS. And for that,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114976:22"/>the <hi>Saints</hi> ſhall praiſe, as 'tis in the Text. HALLELU-JAH, Praiſe ye the Lord; as the 19 of <hi>Revel</hi> ſings concent and conſort to it, <hi>Hallelu-Iah, Hallelu-Iah, Hallelu-Iah, Hallelu-Iah, Hallelu-Iah, Praiſe ye the Lord,</hi> (ſo often is the repetition in the firſt ſix verſes) becauſe the Lord <hi>judgeth the whore, and the beaſt, and the falſe prophet; and kills their army with the edge of the ſword;</hi> as is the cloſe of the Chapter. Then ſhall the Saints begin to have a <hi>Reſt upon earth,</hi> Satan being bound, (<hi>Revel.</hi> 20.) according to the type of the <hi>Iſraelites reſt in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> after their ſubduing thoſe Kings and Nations, as we have a clear hint, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. touched afore. To this things will come, be ſure of it.</p>
            <p>Thus of all the ſeven words of the Doctrine according to the terms of the Text,<note place="margin">The <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>typicall</hi> conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Doctrine and Termes of the Text.</note> conſidered <hi>typically:</hi> Next, a word of all joyncly, conſidered <hi>anti-typically,</hi> and I have done.</p>
            <p>We do (bleſſed be God) bleſs the Lord this day, with <hi>Goſpel-celebrations</hi> of ſinging, praying, preaching, praiſing; as the <hi>Iews</hi> did in this Pſalm, with <hi>religious muſick and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings.</hi> And why praiſe we? Becauſe on <hi>this day,</hi> in a moſt eminent manner and meaſure, <hi>this text is fulfilled in our cars. Bear witneſs, and wonder.</hi> Have not the <hi>Holy people</hi> had <hi>SUCH honour</hi> as to <hi>binde a King and ſome Nobles,</hi> and to <hi>execute judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon them?</hi> Have not the Holy people (as this days mercies tell us) taken <hi>Nobles</hi> priſoners of War (named in our Narrative) and executed vengeance upon the <hi>Nations,</hi> now of the <hi>Scots,</hi> as before of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> enemies to Godlineſs? They all ('tis plain now at laſt) drave on the ſame deſigne, and therefore I juſtly put them together this day; as the <hi>ſword of the Lord and of Gideon</hi> (bleſſed be Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah) hath put them together into the ſame <hi>mortall</hi> incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie to hurt us any more. The meer name <hi>Scots,</hi> pleads but little perſwaſive Oratorie in mine eares, to put the <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality</hi> of them in any higher predicament, then the Engliſh
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:114976:22"/>or Iriſh enemies afore named.<note place="margin">Of theſe we have had ſure intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence; partly by letters, and partly by them that have ſeen and beard the mannerof theſe things, and partly by the carriage of their commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſters here.</note> The <hi>High-landers</hi> are <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</hi> Their <hi>Common-people</hi> (as they confeſſe) are <hi>Vaſſals</hi> to their <hi>Lords;</hi> and we know they are to great vices. The beſt of their <hi>Miniſters,</hi> for the generality, <hi>ſweare</hi> at leaſt petty oathes. Their diſcipline of their <hi>Stoole of repentance,</hi> and their <hi>iron hoop</hi> (which they call <hi>Chriſts yoake</hi>) put upon them that will not aſcend that ſtool to a verbal recantation, are but ridicles. Their <hi>Claſſes</hi> are <hi>Claves,</hi> keyes to ſhut mens mouthes, that nothing may be debated out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures beyond their ſtinted common roade. A wofull hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance to the increaſe of the light of the Goſpell. I will not trouble my ſelf to ſet forth the treacherous and hypocriticall dealings of their Parliament, with ours, becauſe our Parliament hath limb'd them out to the life, in their ſeveral <hi>Declarations,</hi> and <hi>Editions of the Scotiſh Letters and papers;</hi> and our <hi>armyes ſwords</hi> are now convincing them; whom words would never convince. And theſe things hath God adjourned (enquire the cauſe) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till now. Whiles the generality of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> were not Holy people, little was done. Whiles the <hi>Army</hi> in general was not ſo <hi>Holy a people,</hi> little was won. And whiles <hi>Non-Saints,</hi> were the <hi>Non-ſuch</hi> in places of Truſt, there was little hope of any thing to be done. God, you ſee, reſerved <hi>this honour</hi> to the generality of the <hi>Holy-people</hi> in all thoſe rankes. They that have eyes to ſee, let them ſee, leaſt they ſtumble, and tumble, and utterly fall before they open their eyes. For they that uphold the <hi>upholders</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> are oppoſite to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and muſt therefore fall. But they that uphold the preſent Kings of the earth, uphold the <hi>upholders of Antichriſt</hi> (call <hi>experience</hi> to teſtifie); ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe that uphold ſuch upholders, muſt fall. Call <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience</hi> againe to teſtifie this. Nor Engliſh, either <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or <hi>Barons,</hi> or <hi>Bores,</hi> that took part with the late king; nor after
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:114976:23"/>them the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> nor laſt of all the <hi>Scots;</hi> and Scotiſh and Scotified adherents do ſtand. From the Declarations, Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Sermons, (of this third and laſt party named) partly to be ſeen in print, the late proceedings againſt the King, had their firſt maine riſe. Since they have changed their cauſe, God hath changed their ſucceſſe; but they will not ſee it. Therfore that of <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.11. and <hi>chap.</hi> 10.6. threatens them. <hi>Lord, when thy hand is lifted up, they will not ſee; but they ſhall ſee, and be aſhamed, for their envy at the people.</hi> I <hi>will ſend the rod of anger againſt an hypocriticall nation.</hi> The <hi>hypocriticall Phariſees</hi> are by Chriſt <hi>accounted worſe then Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and Harlots.</hi> Lay all together, and the reſult ſoon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, the more the holy people (in place) increaſe, and the hypocriſie of the enemies break forth, to the prejudice of Chriſts intereſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.17.</note> the ſooner they fall before the <hi>Holy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> Is it not yet poſſible for men to ſee that all that will not joyne with the <hi>Holy people,</hi> of <hi>the Parliament, Council, Army, Fleet, Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> fall under them, and fall a maine?</p>
            <p>God ſuffered a long time the <hi>World</hi> to domineer over the <hi>Holy people;</hi> But now God no longer truſts his <hi>Holy people</hi> in the hands of the <hi>World,</hi> but makes the <hi>World</hi> to truſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the hands of the <hi>Holy people.</hi> And the world work themſelves amaine (if men can ſee) into this condition. If <hi>Military</hi> men will not manifeſt themſelves meet to guard the <hi>peace of the ſtate,</hi> Regiments of the <hi>Holy people</hi> muſt. If the great <hi>Dons</hi> will not be fit for place of <hi>Magistrates,</hi> a choice from among the <hi>Holy people</hi> muſt. If <hi>Kings</hi> will not rule the <hi>Holy people</hi> well, the <hi>Holy people</hi> ſhall rule <hi>them</hi> well. If the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation murderouſly rebel, and the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Nation unrighteouſly invade, neither ſubmitting to Equity, though tendred to them; they fall, they ſurely fall, they fully fall before the authority, power and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:114976:23"/>prayers of the <hi>holy people</hi> of <hi>Parliament, Army, magiſtrats, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, Churches, and all ſaints.</hi> And with great reproach, as well as ruine to them that fall.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Ireland</hi> about <hi>Dublin,</hi> neere 19000. fall and fly before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 4000. of ours. In <hi>England,</hi> in the North, neere 31000. <hi>Scotts</hi> invading us, under <hi>Hamilton,</hi> fall and fly before about 8000. of ours. In <hi>Scotland</hi> (as this day remembers) 11000. of ours encounter with 22000. of the Scots (ſome of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſince, confeſſe they were more) and 6000. of ours (thereabout) do the worke to give that numerous Hoſt of <hi>Scotts</hi> the totall Rout.</p>
            <p>Many glorious circumſtances there are, of this laſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw: but becauſe I have been long, and would not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent my reverend Brother that is to follow, I will ſpeake but of one maine one, and that in the way of a <hi>caſe of conſcience</hi> as the nature of it requires.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scottiſh enemie</hi> (wee cannot but ſay) <hi>merited</hi> this their overthrow, by invading us, and that without <hi>warning</hi> of us,<note place="margin">A caſe of Conſcience, <hi>whether the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the</hi> Scots <hi>be the</hi> return of prayers, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Gods mind againſt their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous dealing, or onely a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual event?</note> 
               <hi>refuſing</hi> alſo to give us any ſatisfaction; though both theſe were deſired. They uſed the <hi>meanes</hi> to bring it upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by ſeverall fierce on-ſets upon us, they ſtrikeing the firſt blow. They yet further <hi>purſue</hi> and <hi>ſeeke after</hi> their ruine by a furious march after us netreating, many miles (I name not particulars becauſe ſo excellently ſet down in the <hi>Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> before the Act for this dayes praiſe) And laſt of all (we muſt ſay) they <hi>prayed</hi> for this their ruine implicitly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretatively as the event proves. For they <hi>invoked God</hi> in prayer, making therein their <hi>appeale to God</hi> to determin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and us; as we did (we confeſſe) make the like appeale to him. Behold then (and lay all together) according to their <hi>ſinne</hi> fore-going, (in wronging our Nation; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their following <hi>ohſtinacy</hi> in their ſinne, in refuſing to give ſatisfaction; and according to their <hi>prayers</hi> in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:114976:24"/>that God would take part with the right and oppoſe the wrong doer, hath God dealt with them, and anſwered them, by their ruine. But now ſiince they ſay (in their let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from <hi>Edenborough Caſtle</hi> to our Generall) tis but an <hi>event</hi> of <hi>caſuall</hi> happ; no declaration of the mind of God againſt them. But mark now in anſwer to that but theſe 5. things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Their and their <hi>partyes</hi> (the Scotified in <hi>England</hi>) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, of providences following upon prayer, made in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to thoſe providences. Firſt, when the Scots <hi>Kirk party</hi> prayed that <hi>Hamilton</hi> might not proſper (it ſeems now it was only becauſe hee came againſt us not with their conſent, as <hi>Leven</hi> did this laſt time) and <hi>Hamilton</hi> did not proſper, they cryed it up mightily, with many iterations that his over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw was the returne of <hi>prayer,</hi> and of <hi>their</hi> prayers; we are ſure it was of <hi>ours,</hi> who then prayed and were heard; which with other the like inſtances of our praying and Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering (above farr, what human meanes could effect) as in this laſt overthrow of the Scots, makes us with confidence of faith plead <hi>divine cuſtome,</hi> that providences uſhered in by prayer (pardon the phraſe) are Gods gratious returnes of ſuch prayers. Yea, and we have learned (we truly ſpeak our experience of our ſelvs) that when God doth not anſwer our prayers ſo as we are apt to chooſe, we look upon the inſuing providences of God as a diſtinct returne of our prayers, that then that, and that only and no more, is good for us. Secondly when the Scots immediatly afore their firſt on-ſet upon us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Musſleborough</hi> had had a day of prayer; they did ere they cloſe, undertake, as it were, to propheſie (ſo confident were they of the return of their prayers) that their men ſhould go forth and only <hi>ſtand ſtill</hi> and we ſhould fall before them, and to further encourage them diverſe of their <hi>Miniſters</hi> came with them to the fight, of which we had moſt certain intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, by ſpies, or priſoners taken in that fight or otherwiſe.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114976:24"/>Thirdly, when we were another time retreated on this ſide <hi>Muſſleborough</hi> a party of them comming thither, and finding us gone, they then made great boſt in their prayers and of their prayers that had ſent the <hi>Sectaries</hi> packing; as our men returning thither upon them neer found them at it: to a great terrour on them to a ſuddaine flight; but could not ſo quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and cleanly carry away al, but that our men knew this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage I now mention, and wrote it up to us. Fourthly, when they made their long march after us retreating to <hi>Haddinton,</hi> and thence to <hi>Dunbarre;</hi> then in many expreſſions openly to our <hi>Scouts</hi> as they met, they did infinitly boaſt of their hoped ſucceſſes, as the returne (no doubt) of their prayers: <hi>the Kirk party</hi> contrary to the opinion of the old ſouldiery <hi>Jehu</hi>-like putting on to fight, concluding, as they ſayd, that now they had us in a Corniſh pound. And laſt of all let us not forget the voyce of ſom of our neighbours Scottified miniſters at home, which is but the <hi>eccho</hi> to the Scotts; who upon our retreat to <hi>Dunbarr,</hi> gave thanks publikly as the return of their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and the Scots prayers, that our Army was brought to this paſſe of retreate, to that effect or intent. Which will be further expounded by one of the hearers of thoſe <hi>morning excerciſes,</hi> ſaying to a very godly Freind thus, <q>
                  <hi>Lo you now, Mr. you ſee now what it is for your Army to go againſt the prayers of Gods people, you proſpered indeed againſt the enimie at home, and in Ireland becauſe Gods peoples prayers were not againſt you. But in going againſt the Scotts you go againſt Godly mens prayers, and therefore you ſee what it comes to.</hi>
               </q> To <hi>that effect hee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This Caſe in the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the <hi>Appeale</hi> (I intend it and extend it not further as to debauch Perſons or perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances) is the ſame with the caſe of <hi>Elijah</hi> and <hi>Baals Prieſts,</hi> appealing to God in a way of Prayer (which uſually was conjoyned with Sacrifice, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.) The difference only is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:114976:25"/>but in the degree of the ſigne of Anſwer; that was a <hi>Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle above Nature;</hi> and our deliverance was in a <hi>marvell</hi> many wayes <hi>above Nature:</hi> (as we ſhall ſee preſently.) <hi>Baal Prieſts</hi> were <hi>convinced,</hi> God had determined againſt them: So that we reade not of any <hi>apologie</hi> they could make for themſelves, when they were put to death for their impoſture, 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 18. And truely if <hi>Heathens</hi> had looked on <hi>us,</hi> and the <hi>Scots,</hi> thus ſolemnly appealing, and God thus manifeſtly anſwering, and yet we not agreeing, that it was a manifeſt determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the minde of God: thoſe Heathens doubtleſſe, would either conclude that our God were no God, or elſe that we had no Religion in us. This will be plainer in the next par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Tis mightily conſiderable to our Caſe in hand, that God hath a ſingular regard to any of his <hi>Ordinances,</hi> when men in them make <hi>ſolemn addreſſes</hi> to him, how many failings ſoever there be in the men, and their manner of perſonnance of them. Yea, and we all generally doe thinke ſo; as in the matter of ſwearing men that have no grace for Witneſſe, (which is an ordinance of appeal to God.) We <hi>acquieſce</hi> in their Teſtimonie,<note place="margin">Jonah Chap. 1.</note> as being aſſured ſuch men feare to ſweare falſly, leaſt their implied imprecation ſhould fall upon them. And we ſee often wretched men that dare <hi>ſpeake</hi> falſly, dare not <hi>ſweare</hi> falſly. Now marke in the Story of <hi>Jonah</hi> his Sea-voyage. <hi>Prayer,</hi> and <hi>caſting of lots,</hi> are both Ordinances of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn addreſſes and appeale to God. The <hi>Heathen</hi> Marriners uſe both, <hi>they cryed everie one to his God,</hi> and rouſed up ſleepy <hi>Jonah</hi> alſo to call upon his God; and by common conſent alſo <hi>caſt lots</hi> to find who was the malefactor in the ſhip, that cauſed this tempeſt. Theſe Prayers thus made by theſe <hi>Heathens,</hi> and this lot ſo caſt by the ſame hand, are anſwered by a moſt juſt determination upon <hi>Jonah.</hi> They all <hi>acquieſce</hi> in it as juſt; <hi>Jonah</hi> ſubmits, and is content to be thrown into the Sea, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:114976:25"/>then the ſhip and all the men ſhould periſh. Why ſhould I inlarge upon that which you can eaſily make out your ſelves? And what can you make leſſe of it, but that the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>We</hi> are in <hi>this,</hi> worſe then theſe <hi>Heathens,</hi> if after ſo many dayes of Faſtings and Prayers by both of us appealing to God, God anſwering in a worke of wonder, we ſhould not own it as his Anſwer?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Furthermore, God is not in vain called THE LORD OF HOSTS, (and which is not inconſiderable to the Point in hand, It was our word, the day of Battle, when the hand that had been lift up in Prayer, was now lift up in fight, to make experiment what would be the minde of God in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to thoſe Prayers:) By which <hi>Lord of Hoſts</hi> in the day of our Victory againſt the <hi>Scots,</hi> there were ſo many great things done above all humane Power, as cannot without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie be aſcribed to any, but to the <hi>Lord of Hoſts.</hi> I ſhall rehearſe but ſome of thoſe Particulars we had firſt from the Councill of State, and after from the Parliament.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That 22000. all fully ready for fight, and afore hand with us, and had all advantages of the ground, did not ſtand againſt 6000. of Us. Secondly, not an houre. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Upon this oddes at leaſt 4000. of the <hi>Scots</hi> ſlaine upon the place, and in purſuit. Fourthly, above twice as many taken Priſoners. And that fiftly, when our men many of them were ſickly, many of them wearied with wants, foul weather, and ſome of them (as I know by Letters under their hands) much fainting in their ſpirits, The Enemy much heightned afore the fight, with our long retreat. Sixthly, Not 40. of our men killed. Who would not, who could not ſay, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>Digitus Dei;</hi> here is the very Finger of God appeares in this?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly, the <hi>Parliament</hi> and all their Friends have deepe impreſſions on their hearts, in Prayer, Prayſe, publicke E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:114976:26"/>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that herein was the manifeſt determination of the minde of God againſt the unrighteouſneſſe of the <hi>Scots</hi> deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with us. And ſuch impreſſions as are on Godly mens hearts generally, and in ſolemne addreſſes to God the Search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the heart,<note place="margin">1. John 5.</note> and in publicke Profeſſions before the whole World, are not to be ſlieghted as nothing.</p>
            <p>There is,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle, the Teſtimonie of a Saints owne Spirit, beſide the Spirit of God to be conſidered in his Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence or Diffidence. So that though the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Scottiſh,</hi> owne not this Divine Determination, as from God; but ſome of them (if ſingular Teſtimonie faile me not) in a manner aſcribe it to the <hi>Devill,</hi> alleadging Our Army uſed ſome inchantment, to <hi>know,</hi> or <hi>doe;</hi> and the beſt of them thinke it to be matter of Faith, (as their letters out of <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough</hi> Caſtle intimate) to beleeve this Victory was but as a <hi>Contingencie,</hi> and ſo harden themſelves (I feare) as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did, by means of the <hi>Enchanters,</hi> &amp;c. perhaps to their fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſtruction as he did; yet we cannot but owne it as Gods Determination, and owne it with Admiration, and with the more, the more we thinke of it. Becauſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary minded are onely afflicted in their mindes by this croſſe to their vaine hopes; We are delivered from our rationall feares and reall dangers to our Lives, our Eſtates, our Liberties, Civill and Evangelicall. For they had (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by the Writings in the <hi>Chancellours purſe,</hi> that was tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en in warres brought in the accuſed thing. And had the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of Our retreat laſted but foure dayes longer, I am aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them that know, the <hi>Word</hi> had been given to <hi>England</hi> (according to <hi>Levens</hi> ſpeech at their Councell of Warre, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fight) and the thouſands of <hi>Scotified</hi> and <hi>Royalized</hi> in the ſeverall Counties and Cities in <hi>England</hi> liſted for this purpoſe (whereof I am full ſure) had riſen to wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in the <hi>Scots,</hi> with their accurſed thing. But
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:114976:26"/>now they may keepe it, and without repentance periſh with it.</p>
            <p>O ye <hi>Parliament, People, Magiſtrates, Miniſters,</hi> that will be owned of Chriſt in the glorious times approaching, praiſe yee the Lord, all your dayes. And when you would me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on our deliverance. Reade <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 16. <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. and the <hi>Narrative of the Act</hi> for this Day of Thankeſgiving, and at the end of every Period, ſay, as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136. <hi>For his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy endures for ever.</hi> And then cloſe with the Text, <hi>This honour have all his Saints, Praiſe ye the Lord,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>This Auther hath latly Publiſhed a ſmall Treatiſe intituled, <hi>The miſcheife of mixt Communions,</hi> fully diſcuſſed; Wherein all Arguments on both ſides are fully handled: ſould by <hi>William Raybould, at</hi> the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorne in Pauls Church-Yard.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
